

                                                                                             2010
















        Virginia Environmental





        Attitudes Survey








                                                                       T  e        n v i r o n m e n T and
                                                                          he
                                                                  e  conomic            d   evelopmenT

 = Page 1 =







        Introduction

               This is the second of three planned statewide surveys   much in the next ten years. Virginians think the Chesapeake
        on the public’s perception of the natural environment in Virginia.   Bay and the state’s historic rivers are the most important
        The first study in 2009 focused on climate change and examined   natural resources, and they worry most about their health.
        what Virginians know about it, their personal environmental   They worry least about the health of the state’s mountain
        behavior, and their views on public policy related to climate   ranges.
        change. This second study focuses on economic approaches to      A strong majority of Virginians think state government
        dealing with Virginia’s environment and climate change as well   has a role to play in improving the environment and are very
        as assessing the health of the state’s natural environment and   supportive of approaches to dealing with the environment that
        evaluating the most important natural resources in Virginia.    are also good for the economy and create clean jobs. Virginians
               Overall, Virginians give the quality of the state’s natural   also support governmental actions that might lead to cleaner,
        environment an average grade and don’t think it will change   more reliable, and safer energy in the future.
        The health of Virginia’s environment

               In 2009 Virginians gave the state’s natural environment   or “F.”   What will the state’s natural environment look like in
        an average grade of 2.6, or “C”. In 2010 the average grade dropped   ten years? Nearly six in ten Virginians think it will be about the
        slightly to 2.4 (See Figure 1). Only six percent of Virginians give   same as it is now (See Figure 2). Nearly two in ten say it will
        the natural environment a grade of “A”, while just over three in   be much worse while just under two in ten say it will be much
        ten give it a grade of “B.” About one in ten give it a grade of “D”   better than it is now.



                                                                ’

                           f igures  1 & 2: a ssessmenT of  irginias naTural environmenT and prospecTs for The fuTure
                                                        v





                                                                      Much Better     17.5%
                "A"     6.1%
                "B"                      31.9%                      About the Same                         57.9%
                "C"                                51.1%
                "D"      7.3%                                         Much Worse       19.3%
                "F"  1.3%
            Unsure (vol.)  1.5%                                      Unsure (vol.)  3.6%
           DK/no answer  0.7%                                        DK/no answer  1.7%
                  0%    10%   20%   30%   40%    50%   60%
                                                                           0%   10%   20%  30%  40%   50%  60%  70%
        Virginia’s Most important natural resources
                                                                        17.5%
                                                   Much Better
                                                About the Same
                                                                                                    57.9%
               Virginians have a strong affinity for the Chesapeake Bay      Not surprisingly, Virginians are worried about the
        and its coastal tributaries. Asked to indicate their first and second   health of the Chesapeake Bay and the state’s historic rivers
                                                  Much Worse
                                                                         19.3%
        most important natural resource in the state from a list of six   3.6%  more than they are other natural resources. Asked to rate the
                                                  Unsure (vol.)
        natural resources, a combined 47.3% chose the Chesapeake Bay  1.7%  health of the same six natural resources using a scale of 1 to 5,
                                                 DK/no answer
                                                                  with 1 representing “very poor” health and 5 representing “very
        (See Figure 3) while a combined 37.7% chose the state’s historic   10%  20%  30%  40%  50%  60%   70%
                                                          0%
        rivers such as the James, York and Potomac. Forests and public   good” health, the Chesapeake Bay and historic rivers tied with
        lands received the lowest combined score at 20.2%.        the lowest average rating of 2.8 (See Figure 4).



                                                  f igures  3 & 4: m osT i m p o r T a n T naTural resources and Their healTh



            The Chesapeake Bay and …              47.3%
                                                                              Mountain ranges             3.70
                 Historic rivers             37.7%
                                                                            Parks and open space         3.50
                Mountain ranges           30.9%
             Parks and open space      25.0%                               Forests and public lands     3.40
           Atlantic ocean and barrier …  20.3%                        Atlantic ocean and barrier islands  3.00
            Forests and public lands  20.2%                                    Historic rivers      2.80
              All equally important  15.9%
                                                                    The Chesapeake Bay and its tributaries  2.80
                         0%   10%  20%  30%  40%  50%
                                                                                       1      2      3     4      5
        a pril  2010                                W ason  c enTer for  p ublic  p olic y  -  v irginia  e n v i r o n m e n T a l  a TTiTudes  s ur vey


 = Page 2 =







      The Environment and Economic Development

              By  strong  majorities,  Virginians  think  their  state   important environmental and economic goals for the future,
       government has a great deal or some responsibility to create   new jobs and business opportunities in renewable energy and
       policies that might address climate change and improve the state’s   conservation toped the list, followed by reducing dependency
       environment. About two in ten Virginians say the state has little or   on foreign oil.
       no responsibility to do this.                                    Finally, Virginians favor working now to develop new
              What kind of policies do Virginians support? Asked to   energy sources, even paying more for energy today because
       indicate their first and second choices for policy approaches   they see it as in the state’s long term interest. Strong majorities
       they would like to see the state pursue, Virginians put greater   are willing to pay more for energy now as an investment in
       energy efficiency and creating more clean jobs at the top of   cleaner, more reliable, affordable, and safer energy down
       the list (See Figure 5). At the bottom of the list is encouraging   the road. Even stronger majorities think it is in Virginia’s best
       greater environmental stewardship. Clearly Virginians like the   interest to develop new sources of energy that are cleaner,
       opportunity to be environmentally responsible in a way that is   reliable, affordable, and safer regardless of whether or not
       also economically beneficial. Further evidence of this is seen in   climate change is happening or not. Virginians clearly see the
       Figure 6.  When asked to indicate their first and second most   long-term benefit of investing in clean energy today.


        f igures  5 & 6: T
                        he environmenT and economic developmenT


             More energy efficient            49.5%                Creating jobs in renewable         64.4%
           Creating more clean jobs         44.3%                  energy and conservation
         Cleaning up the environment  30.8%                          Ending dependence on           58.3%
                                                                        foreign oil
         Reduce energy consumption  22.5%
            Improving health of the …  20.4%                     Reducing pollution of air and   49.0%
                                                                       water
         Environmental stewardship  13.8%                         Reducing causes of climate
                  All of them  11.9%                                   change            20.5%
                        0%      20%     40%     60%                              0%    20%   40%   60%   80%

      Conclusion

              Virginians value the state’s natural environment, think   clean energy jobs.
       it could be better, but do not expect much improvement in it      Taken as a whole, this study suggests public support
       over the next decade. Virginians also express strong support for   for policies designed to both care for the state’s environment
       governmental action to improve the quality of the state’s natural   and natural resources while at the same time taking advantage
       environment, especially if that action also leads to improved   of economic opportunities around the development of a clean
       economic opportunity in renewable energy, conservation, and   energy economy.


       QuESTION: How much responsibility do you think Virginia’s government has to create policies that could address the issue of climate
       change and improve the state’s environment? Would you say a great deal of responsibility, some responsibility, little responsibility, or
       no responsibility?
       37.2% Great Deal     40.5% Some     12.3% Little     8.3% None     1.6% unsure/DK/no answer
                                                            ---
       STATEmENT: Slightly higher energy costs today are worth the investment if they lead to energy that is cleaner, reliable, affordable, and
       safer down the road.
       25.4% Strongly agree     56.0% Agree     12.4% Disagree     4.6% Strongly Disagree     1.6% unsure/DK/no answer
                                                            ---
       STATEmENT: Taking smart, effective action now to develop new energy sources will result in energy that is cleaner, reliable, afford-
       able, and safer in the long run.
       31.9% Strongly agree     56.9% Agree     7.6% Disagree     1.6% Strongly Disagree     2.0% unsure/DK/no answer
                                                            ---
       STATEmENT: Regardless of whether there is or isn’t climate change, it is still in Virginia’s best interest to develop new sources of
       energy that are cleaner, reliable, affordable, and safer.
       42.4% Strongly agree     48.8% Agree     5.7% Disagree     1.4% Strongly Disagree     1.8% unsure/DK/no answer



        W ason   c enTer for  p ublic   p olic y   -  v irginia  e n v i r o n m e n T a l  a TTiTudes  s ur vey    a  pril  2010


 = Page 3 =


                    Judy Ford Wason Center for Public Policy
                             Christopher Newport University
                                                   mcmuran Hall 264
                                                   1 university Place
                                           Newport News, VA 23606-2998
                            phone: (757) 594-8033  -  e-mail: wasoncenter@cnu.edu
                                                  http://cpp.cnu.edu














































     Methodology



     The 2010 Virginia Environmental Attitudes Survey is a public opinion survey of 719 randomly
     selected registered Virginia voters conducted by land line telephone between march 17-26, 2010.
     The data reported here are weighted on sex, age, and region of residence to reflect as closely as
     possible the demographic composition of Virginia adults 18 and older. Percentages may not equal
     100 due to rounding. Results for the full sample have a margin of error of plus or minus 3.6% at
     the 95% confidence level. This means for the full sample we can be 95% confident that the error
     attributable to sampling and other random effects is plus or minus 3.6%. In addition to sampling
     error, the other potential sources of error include non-response, question wording, and interviewer
     error. Where percentages for subgroups are reported, the margin of error would be higher. The poll
     was designed by Quentin Kidd of the Wason Center for Public Policy at CNu and conducted by
     the Institute of Public Opinion at muhlenberg College. For information or requests call (757) 594-
     8033 or e-mail qkidd@cnu.edu. Full toplines and cross-tabs can be found at http://cpp.cnu.edu.
     Funding for the VEAS is provided in part by a grant from the Virginia Environmental Endowment.

 = Page 4 =
