<metadata xml:lang="en"><Esri><CreaDate>20120108</CreaDate><CreaTime>08362900</CreaTime><ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat><ArcGISstyle>ISO 19139 Metadata Implementation Specification</ArcGISstyle><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><ArcGISProfile>ISO19139</ArcGISProfile><DataProperties><lineage editorFillOnly="True"><Process export="False" Name="" ToolSource=""/></lineage></DataProperties></Esri><dataIdInfo><idCitation><resTitle>AHPS Shapefile - Forecast</resTitle></idCitation><idPurp>NOAA’s National Weather Service (NWS) provides a wide variety of hydrologic and hydro-meteorologic forecasts and information through the web. These web-based resources originate at NWS field, national center, and headquarters offices and are designed to meet the needs of a wide range of users from someone who needs the five-day forecast for a river near his home to the technically advanced water manager who needs probabilistic information to make long-term decisions on allocation of flood mitigation resources or water supply. The NWS will continue to expand and refine all types of web products to keep pace with the demands of all types of users.</idPurp><idAbs>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;A shapefile of river and lake forecast which is updated every 15-minutes&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</idAbs><idCredit>National Weather Service collaborates with many federal, state, and local agencies in providing you accurate and updated information. This collaboration, while avoiding duplication of efforts, enables us to pool resources to fulfill our mission objectives of providing forecasts and warnings for the protection of life and property, and the enhancement of the national economy. NWS data and products form a national information database and infrastructure which can be used by other governmental agencies, the private sector, the public, and the global community.

Our partners include many federal, state, and local agencies and organizations. This brief introduction will help you to understand the nature of our partnerships and provide a link to their web sites for more information. </idCredit><dataLang><languageCode value="en"/></dataLang><idPoC><rpOrgName>NWS Office of Climate, Water, &amp; Weather Services (OCWWS)</rpOrgName><rpIndName>WFO Hydrologic Forecast System (WHFS)</rpIndName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><eMailAdd>whfs@noaa.gov</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="007"/></role></idPoC><resMaint><maintFreq><MaintFreqCd value="009"/></maintFreq><maintScp><ScopeCd value="005"/></maintScp></resMaint><tpCat><TopicCatCd value="012"/></tpCat></dataIdInfo><mdLang><languageCode value="en"/></mdLang><mdContact><rpIndName>WFO Hydrologic Forecast System (WHFS)</rpIndName><rpOrgName>NWS Office of Climate, Water, &amp; Weather Services (OCWWS)</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><eMailAdd>whfs@noaa.gov</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="007"/></role></mdContact><mdMaint><maintFreq><MaintFreqCd value="009"/></maintFreq><maintScp><ScopeCd value="005"/></maintScp></mdMaint><dqInfo><dataLineage><dataSource editorFillOnly="True"/><prcStep editorFillOnly="True"/></dataLineage><dqScope><scpLvl><ScopeCd value="005"/></scpLvl></dqScope></dqInfo><eainfo><detailed editorFillOnly="True"><enttyp><enttypl>GaugeLID</enttypl><enttypd>National Weather Service Location Identifier (NWSLI).</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Stage</enttypl><enttypd>Level of the water surface of a river or stream above an established datum at a given location.</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Location</enttypl><enttypd>Location name of the gauge site.</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Latitude</enttypl><enttypd>Latitude of the gauge site.</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Longitude</enttypl><enttypd>Longitude of the gauge site.</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Waterbody</enttypl><enttypd>Name of water body (river, stream, or lake).</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>State</enttypl><enttypd>U.S. State abbreviation. </enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Forecast</enttypl><enttypd>Maximum forecasted river, stream, or lake value</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>FcstTime</enttypl><enttypd>The Year-Month-Day and time in Universal Time Coordinated (UTC) of the maximum forecasted value</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Units</enttypl><enttypd>Unit of measurement for observed value (FT = U.S. Feet, CFS = Cubic Feet per Second, KCFS = 1000 Cubic Feet per Second).</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Action</enttypl><enttypd>Action Stage or Flow - The stage or flow which, when reached by a rising stream, represents the level where the NWS or a partner/user needs to take some type of mitigation action in preparation for possible signif¬icant hydrologic activity. The appropriate action is usually defined in a weather forecast office (WFO) hydrologic services manual.</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Flood</enttypl><enttypd>Flood Stage or Flow - An established gage height or flow for a given location above which a rise in water surface level begins to create a hazard to lives, property, or commerce. The issuance of flood (or in some cases flash flood) warnings is linked to flood stage or flood flow. Not necessarily the same as bankfull stage.</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Moderate</enttypl><enttypd>Moderate Flooding - The inundation of secondary roads; transfer to higher elevation necessary to save property -- some evacuation may be required.</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Major</enttypl><enttypd>Major Flooding - A general term including extensive inundation and property damage. (Usually characterized by the evacuation of people and livestock and the closure of both primary and secondary roads.).</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>URL</enttypl><enttypd>Uniform Resource Locator (URL) to the AHPS hydrograph page for a specific gauge location.</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>WFO</enttypl><enttypd>Weather Forecast Office (WFO) - Type of National Weather Service office is responsible for issuing advisories, warnings, statements, and short term forecasts for its county warning area.</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>HorizontalDatum </enttypl><enttypd>The type of horizontal control datum of the gauge location latitude and longitude.</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>FcstIssunc</enttypl><enttypd>The forecast issuance Year-Month-Day and time in Universal Time Coordinated (UTC).</enttypd></enttyp></detailed></eainfo><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005"/></mdHrLv></metadata>
