









                                                                                                Virginia DCR
                                                                              Planning & Recreation Resources
                                                                                         203 Governor Street
                                                                                         Richmond, VA 23219



                                    A GUIDE TO CITIZEN INVOLVEMENT IN THE
                                       SCENIC RIVER DESIGNATION PROCESS


               In 1970 legislation, authorizing the establishment of a Virginia Scenic Rivers System was
               enacted by the General Assembly. The legislation set up a framework whereby the Department
               of Conservation and Recreation (DCR) was charged with conducting studies and presenting
               reports and recommendations to the legislature concerning potential additions to the System. The
               General Assembly must then consider the report and take legislative action to designate a river as
               scenic. Following a series of unsuccessful designation attempts, it became apparent that future
               attempts would have to go far beyond the mere preparation of a report in order to be successful.
               Political reality dictated a need for development of a strong local citizen base for support of the
               candidate river designation in the jurisdictions where the candidate river was located.

               In response to the initial challenges, Department staff began working with local advisory groups
               to add candidate rivers to the Scenic River System. Since the program’s inception, designation of
               some Scenic Rivers and two (2) Historic Rivers
               [ http://www.dcr.virginia.gov/recreational_planning/documents/srlist.pdf ] now comprise the
               Scenic River System. This paper is not intended to be all-inclusive, but rather to give potential
               interest groups or individuals some idea of the amount and type of work involved in obtaining
               Scenic River designation.

               The  initial step  for individuals or groups interested in the possible designation of a river is to
               contact the DCR Division of Planning and Recreation Resources. After preliminary
               conversations, a meeting among all interested parties to discuss the designation process is a next
               logical step. The purpose of the initial meeting is actually fourfold:


                       1. To discuss the Virginia Scenic Rivers Program and the designation process.

                       2. To organize a local advisory committee.

                       3. To formalize a working relationship between the advisory committee and the DCR
                          program staff.

                       4. To outline a preliminary work plan.

               The local advisory committee may be composed of a combination of local officials, civic leaders,
               riparian landowners, conservation interests, and other citizens. If properly structured, this
               committee should represent a variety of interests, thereby broadening its base of support and
               providing a vital liaison with as many local groups as possible. Before an evaluation of the
               qualities of a potential designated river, DCR needs, in hand,  a letter  from the Board of
               Supervisors or County Administrator requesting that a study be conducted.



               Rev. 01/24/13                                                                         1 of 3

 = Page 1 =







               Once the request is sent and the local advisory committee formed, the advisory committee will
               have two primary functions:


                   1. Preparation for  the evaluation  and field study -- Initial information needs to be gathered
                       for the study report and provided to DCR in advance of their field visit(s). Preparations
                       need to be made for the field visit through organization of boats, shuttles, and guides.
                       Additionally, advisory committee representatives need to be ready to participate in the
                       actual field study.
                   2. Development of   community-wide support     -- This is necessary to ensure the success of

                       the designation attempt.

               The first of these responsibilities,  the evaluation , is the easiest and least time consuming. It
               involves the gathering of information on natural, historical, and recreational features of the river
               that make it worthy of inclusion in the System. This information is provided to DCR staff in
               preparation for the evaluation field trip(s) and the resulting writing of the final report. Advisory
               committee facilitation of and participation in the field visit also deserves emphasis.

               Developing a necessary base of  support  for a designation is considerably more involved.
               Support from four (4) sectors of the community is essential to success. These four sectors or
               groups are:

                   1. Riparian landowners


                   2. Civic groups

                   3. Local Boards of Supervisors and other affected local government entities

                   4. Local members of the General Assembly

               The support of  riparian landowners  is critical to the success of a designation attempt.
               Consequently, identifying those landowners should be one of the advisory committee’s top
               priorities. Copies of tax maps and the names and mailing addresses of property owners are
               usually easily obtainable at the office of the County Commissioner of Revenue. Once riparian
               landowners are identified, meeting with each one is the best way to ensure that the Scenic River
               concept and its relationship to owners is understood. If personal contact with all landowners is
               not possible, each should receive a letter, drafted by the committee, discussing the program and
               inviting questions. Included in the letter could be an invitation to a  community meeting  where
               questions can be answered within the format of a public forum. At the very least, those riparian
               landowners thought to have the greatest degree of local influence should be individually
               contacted and asked to lend assistance and support to the advisory committee.

               Although it may prove to be a formidable task, keeping landowners well informed throughout
               the study and designation process is essential. It may be useful to set up periodic informational
               meetings to ensure that landowners and other local citizens have ample opportunity to express
               their concerns and/or support.

               Other important sources for contacts that can be of significant assistance in developing a broad
               base of support are local  civic groups  and organizations. These groups can serve as an effective
               means of disseminating information about the scenic river proposal. The opportunity to makes
               presentations should not be overlooked. Groups such as Ruritans, garden clubs, historical




               Rev. 01/24/13                                                                         2 of 3

 = Page 2 =







               societies, sportsmen’s groups, Chambers of Commerce, and conservation groups can become
               enthusiastic supporters of the designation process. Presentations not only raise the level of public
               awareness but they also help prevent misinformation. In addition, additional proactive supporters
               may be gained who can be counted on for meetings or hearings with local governing bodies.

               In addition to informing and educating the riparian landowners and local civic groups, local
               governing bodies  must be kept fully informed and up-to-date on critical issues involved in the
               designation attempt. It is beneficial to schedule an informal meeting to let them know a
               designation is being considered, to set up a means of communication, and then to continue
               keeping them informed on study progress. Also, tell them of potential points of contention as
               soon as possible. Thus, when their support is formally requested, they will be aware of the issues.
               The unqualified support of local government is one of the most critical factors associated with
               the passage of scenic river designation.

               When and if  opposition to scenic designation  surfaces, whether from individuals or
               organizations, every effort should be made to personally address all complaints. This is
               necessary for two reasons. First, misconceptions and misinformation need to be straightened out
               before they become widespread. Second, complaints give proponents information on the primary
               concerns of opponents and, therefore, ideas on how to prepare an effective response.

               Once the study has been completed and the report and designation recommendations finalized,
               resolutions and letters of support  should be solicited from as many governmental and civic
               groups and individuals as possible. These letters and resolutions will become part of the official
               record when and if a public hearing on the designation recommendation is held.

               Local members of the  General Assembly  should also be notified of the designation efforts, as
               their support is essential to your cause. Their participation will be necessary in order to introduce
               the designation legislation and support it as it goes through the legislative process. You should
               find that when there is strong local support for scenic rivers, local legislators are usually pleased
               to introduce the necessary bills when requested to do so by the local governing body. DCR staff
               can provide sample “boilerplate” legislation.

               For more information contact:
               Virginia Department of Conservation and Recreation
               Planning and Recreation Resources
               203 Governor Street, Suite 326
               Richmond, Virginia 23219

               Lynn M. Crump, LA, ASLA, Environmental Programs Planner
               (804) 786- 5054 fax (804) 371-7899  Lynn.Crump@dcr.virginia.gov













               Rev. 01/24/13                                                                         3 of 3

 = Page 3 =
