





                     FEDERAL EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT AGENCY (FEMA) HAZUS - CRITICAL FACILITIES



                   TABLE OF CONTENTS


                     1. GEOGRAPHIC COVERAGE
                     2. REQUEST FOR ACKNOWLEDGEMENT


                     3. ABSTRACT

                     4. DATASET PARAMETERS
                     5. DATASET ANALYSIS AND MANIPULATIONS


                     6. DATA DESCRIPTION

                     7. GEOGRAPHIC AND SPATIAL INFORMATION

                     8. QUALITY CONTROL AND QUALITY ASSURANCE
                     9. DATA ACCESS AND DISTRIBUTION


                     10.TABLE OF ACRONYMS

                     11.CONTACT INFORMATION

                  GEOGRAPHIC COVERAGE

                  Coastal Shoreline Counties
                  A county is considered a Coastal Shoreline County if it is directly adjacent to the open
                  ocean, major estuaries, or the Great Lakes.  These counties are considered to be most
                  directly affected by issues pertaining to the coast.   Click here  for more information.

                  Coastal Watershed Counties
                  A county is considered a Coastal Watershed County if one of the following criteria is met:
                  (1) at a minimum, 15 percent of the county’s total land area is located within a coastal
                  watershed or (2) a portion of, or an entire county accounts for at least 15 percent of a
                  coastal watershed. The 15-percent rule was selected as an appropriate level for capturing
                  counties with a significant impact on coastal and ocean resources.  Click here  for more
                  information.

                  Coastal States
                  All states (30) that are directly adjacent to the open ocean or the Great Lakes, as well
                  Washington DC, Puerto Rico, and US Virgin Islands.

                  Coastal Portion of Coastal States
                  A state by state aggregation of all Coastal Shoreline Counties (see definition above)

                  Coastal Zone Boundaries
                  The area contained within the Coastal Zone as defined by each state participating in the
                  Coastal Zone Management Act (subject to change).   For a complete description of the
                  methods used by each state with a Coastal Zone Management Program see the     coastal
                  zone definition for each state .

                  FEMA Special Flood Hazard Area
                  Areas subject to 1-percent annual chance (100-year) coastal floods as determined by the
                  Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA) through the National Flood Insurance
                  Program (NFIP).   Click here  for more information.



 = Page 1 =






                  USGS 8-Digit Hydrologic Unit Code (HUC)
                  USGS has subdivided hydrologic units into a series of successively smaller levels, with the
                  8-digit HUC as the smallest.  The 8-digit HUC is a geographic area representing part or all
                  of a surface drainage basin, a combination of drainage basins, or a distinct hydrologic
                  feature, often referred to as a watershed ( http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/huc.html ).

                  National Estuary Research Reserve System (NERRS) Target Watersheds
                  The  National Estuarine Research Reserve System  (NERRS) is a network of reserves
                  dedicated to long-term research, monitoring, education and resource stewardship. Most
                  NERRS units have delineated an associated target watershed that most directly impacts
                  reserve.  The remaining five NERRS units do not have a target watershed; they are:
                  Kachemak Bay, Mission Aransas, Narragansett Bay, Waquoit Bay, and Lake Superior.

                  National Estuary Research Reserve System (NERRS) Large Watersheds
                  For each of  National Estuarine Research Reserve System  ( NERRS) units and their target
                  watersheds (where applicable), large estuarine watersheds have been delineated using a
                  flow analysis based on a 30-meter digital elevation model corresponding most closely to
                  the boundaries of USGS 8-digit Hydrologic Unit Code (HUC) watersheds.

                  US EPA National Estuary Program Study Areas
                  The mission of the  National Estuary Program  (NEP) is to protect and restore America’s
                  nationally significant estuaries. Each NEP has a designated study area and develops and
                  implements a Comprehensive Conservation and Management Plan for that area. Each NEP
                  has a single study area, with the exception of the Puget Sound NEP, which has divided its
                  study area into seven sub-systems.

                  US EPA National Estuary Program Watersheds
                  The  National Estuary Program  (NEP) has identified the estuarine and fluvial drainage areas
                  associated with each of their  program unit study areas. These larger watersheds were
                  delineated so the NEPs can better understand pressures created upstream of their study
                  areas, providing critical information to successfully implement their Comprehensive
                  Conservation and Management Plans.

                  50-Mile Buffer Area from the
                  Coastline
                  The area within a 50 mile fixed-distance from the coastline.

                  Hurricane Prone Areas
                  The American Society of Civil Engineers (ASCE) delineates hurricane prone areas of the
                  eastern U.S. that are vulnerable to hurricane-force winds (90 mph or greater basic wind
                  speed).

                  REQUEST FOR ACKNOWLEDGMENT

                  NOAA requests that all individuals who download data acknowledge the source of these
                  data in any reports, papers, or presentation. If you publish these data, please include a
                  statement similar to: “Some or all of the data described in this article were produced by
                  the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, National Ocean Service.

 = Page 2 =






                  ABSTRACT

                  The critical facilities data came from FEMA’s HAZUS database and represent available
                  information circa 2011. A critical facility is defined as a structure that, if flooded, would
                  present an immediate threat to life, public health, and safety. The data may not be
                  exhaustive, more thorough data exist both nationally and at the local level. HAZUS breaks
                  critical facilities into two groups: essential facilities and high potential loss (HPL) facilities.
                  Essential facilities include hospitals, medical clinics, schools, fire stations, police stations
                  and emergency operations facilities. High potential loss facilities include dams, levees,
                  military installations, nuclear power plants and hazardous material sites.

                  Within HAZUS, the lifeline inventory is divided between transportation and utility lifeline
                  systems. There are seven (7) transportation systems that include highways, railways, light
                  rail, bus, ports, ferry and airports. There are six (6) utility systems that include potable
                  water, wastewater, natural gas, crude & refined oil, electric power and communications.

                  For STICS purposes, the lifeline inventory systems are also called critical facilities. In total,
                  STICS has selected 18 systems or critical facilities to obtain counts of them in all of the
                  STICS jurisdictions. In alphabetical order, these systems are:

                  Airport facilities, bus facilities, medical facilities, communication facilities, dams, electrical
                  power facilities, emergency operation facilities, fire stations, hazardous material sites,
                  highway bridges, oil systems facilities, police stations, port facilities, potable water
                  facilities, railways facilities, railways bridges, schools, wastewater facilities.

                  For more information about the FEMA HAZUS Critical Facility Inventory and the
                  Transportation and Utility Lifeline Inventory, refer to the  HAZUS  document (The ShakeOut
                  Scenario - Supplemental Study) prepared by MMI engineering, Inc.

                  Many of the goals of those involved in environmental management and policy include
                  finding the balance in the coexistence of natural ecosystems and human society, therefore
                  a complete picture of the geographic patterns of human activity and its relationship to the
                  coastal environment is needed. Critical facilities play a central role in disaster response
                  and recovery. Understanding which facilities are exposed, and the degree of that
                  exposure, can help reduce or eliminate service interruptions and costly redevelopment.
                  Incorporating this information and development planning helps communities get back on
                  their feet.

                  Keywords
                  socioeconomic, HAZUS, Critical Facilities, flooding

                  DATA ANALYSIS AND MANIPULATIONS

                  The Critical Facilities data were obtained in several ESRI geo-database tables by State. A
                  python script was developed to create a single national shapefile for each of the 18
                  critical facilities selected for STICS. An ESRI Model builder script was then developed to
                  tag each of the 18 national critical facilities to each of the STICS jurisdictions. A SAS
                  macro was then written to read the .dbf file of the shapefiles to obtain both the counts

 = Page 3 =






                  of critical facilities on each of the STICS jurisdictions and to develop the final data
                  tables.




                  QUALITY CONTROL AND QUALITY ASSURANCE

                  Counts of certain critical facilities in certain counties were compared against similar

                  counts foundin Internet sites. The differences found were in the range of 0.5% difference.

                  All of the data reported in these data files met the QA specifications.

                  DATA ACCESS
                  Data can be downloaded from the web at   http://csc.noaa.gov/digitalcoast/dataregistry/#/
                  A full data dictionary can be found from the web at
                  http://csc.noaa.gov/htdata/SocioEconomic/CriticalFacilities/CriticalFacilities_DataDictiona
                  ry.pdf


                  CONTACT INFORMATION
                  For more information, contact Jeffery Adkins at jeff.adkins@noaa.gov


 = Page 4 =
