
























                                                                             S
                                              C
                       L ANDSCAPE  LASSIFICATION  YSTEM FOR
                                                      V  IRGINIA



                 A public resource presented by the Virginia Wind Energy Collaborative to
                    facilitate the inclusion of environmental information into macro-siting
                                 decisions with regard to utility-scale wind power


                                                         May 2005








               The  Landscape Classification System for Virginia  (LCS) comprises two main components. The foundation
               of the resource is a collection of geographical information system (GIS) data that describes the Virginia
               wind resource, and layers upon it multiple data sets that identify areas of environmental sensitivity. The
               document provided here is intended to describe the significance of the data layers, it relies extensively
               upon definition of land use categories presented to members of the Virginia Wind Energy Collaborative
                                                       †
               (VWEC) by an environmental working group.   In some instances, VWEC and the working group differ in
                                                                                                          ‡
               opinion regarding the inclusion of certain land use types in specific landscape classification categories.
               The Virginia Wind Energy Collaborative presents this document and associated materials reflecting its
               recommendations to the community at large to better inform responsible wind power development in
               Virginia.


               †   The members of the VWEC Environmental Working Group and their affiliations are listed in Appendix 2 of this
               document.
               ‡  Some members of the working group re-organized and have recommended another version of the LCS embedded
               within a supplementary document that contains materials inconsistent with the charter of the working group set forth
               in July 2003. The Virginia Wind Energy Collaborative is not associated with this newly-formed working group, nor
               does it endorse the materials it presents, notwithstanding any suggested affiliation.




 = Page 1 =







                           C
               T ABLE OF  ONTENTS
               OBJECTIVES AND SCOPE      .....................................................................................................................................2


               BACKGROUND     ..........................................................................................................................................................2
               INTRODUCTION TO THE LANDSCAPE CLASSIFICATION SYSTEM FOR VIRGINIA             ...............................3

               LANDSCAPE CLASSIFICATION SYSTEM FOR VIRGINIA          ..............................................................................6

                  U NSUITABLE     APPED .............................................................................................................................................6
                            : M
                    National Park Service – Appalachian National Scenic Trail and 5-mile buffer zone............................6
                    National Park Service – Blue Ridge Parkway......................................................................................7
                    National Park Service – Shenandoah National Park (SNP).................................................................7
                    U.S. Forest Service – Wilderness Areas..............................................................................................7
                    U.S. Forest Service – National Scenic Areas.......................................................................................8
                    U.S. Forest Service – Special Biologic Areas (SBAs)..........................................................................8
                    U.S. Forest Service – Inventoried Roadless Areas (IRAs)...................................................................9
                    U.S. Forest Service – Research Natural Areas (RNAs).....................................................................10
                    U.S. Forest Service – Wilderness Study Areas..................................................................................10
                    U.S. Forest Service – Inventoried Old Growth Forest........................................................................10
                    Virginia Department of Conservation and Recreation, Division of Natural Heritage – State Parks
                    and Natural Area Preserves...............................................................................................................11
                    Virginia Outdoor Foundation (VOF) Easements................................................................................11
                    U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service National Wildlife Refuges...................................................................12
                    The Nature Conservancy Preserves..................................................................................................12
                    Submerged Aquatic Vegetation..........................................................................................................12
                                        U
                              P
                                            C
                  F LAGGED FOR  OTENTIAL  SE  ONFLICT .............................................................................................................13
                    National Park Service – Appalachian National Scenic Trail and 5 to 10-mile buffer zone.................13
                    The Nature Conservancy Ecoregional Portfolio Sites........................................................................14
                    Virginia Department of Conservation and Recreation, Division of Natural Heritage – Heritage
                    Sites....................................................................................................................................................14
                    U.S. Forest Service – Candidate Wilderness Areas..........................................................................14
                    U.S. Forest Service – Uninventoried Roadless Areas.......................................................................15
                    U.S. Forest Service – Remaining National Forest Lands...................................................................15
                    Virginia Department of Game and Inland Fisheries Wildlife Management Areas..............................16
                    Virginia Department of Forestry State Forests...................................................................................16
                    Cold Water Streams...........................................................................................................................16
                  U NCLASSIFIED ........................................................................................................................................................17

               APPENDIX 1: DATA DICTIONARY     ......................................................................................................................18

               APPENDIX 2: MEMBERS OF THE VIRGINIA WIND ENERGY COLLABORATIVE ENVIRONMENTAL
               WORKING GROUP     ..................................................................................................................................................25




 = Page 2 =








                                    S
               O  BJECTIVES AND  COPE
               The purpose of this report and associated databases is to support efforts on the part of
               the wind energy community to recognize, avoid, and minimize adverse environmental
               impacts arising from utility-scale wind energy development in Virginia. This report and
               the resources it presents and describes are designed to achieve the following
               objectives:
                •    provide a readily accessible environmental database to facilitate macro-siting
                   decisions for utility-scale wind energy developments so that impacts on sites with
                   significant natural resource values are minimized, and

                •    provide contact information for agencies and organizations with environmental
                   conservation and protection mandates affected by the development of potential wind
                   energy sites.

               The goal of this project is to provide a decision-support tool to facilitate siting of utility-
               scale wind energy facilities. This project is focused solely on consideration of impacts
               potentially associated with utility-scale wind systems. This document is not intended for
               direct application to small wind energy systems. Although some opinions differ between
               members of the working group and members of the Virginia Wind Energy Collaborative
               who reviewed the document, broad consensus was reached on the fact that the
               identification of areas of environmental sensitivity would be beneficial to environmental
               groups as well as wind developers, state and local agencies, and citizens of the
               Commonwealth of Virginia.

               B ACKGROUND

               Renewable energy offers the promise that our society’s growing needs for energy might
               be met, at least in part, in a clean and sustainable manner. Of the many sources of
               renewable energy, wind is now the least expensive to produce and the most abundant,
               with the potential to supply a significant portion of the electricity demand in the United
               States. Although no utility-scale wind energy facilities are now operating in the
               Commonwealth, several sites are being considered in the coastal and mountain
               regions. Among the factors likely to accelerate the pace and increase the extent of wind
               energy development in Virginia are the Renewable Portfolio Standards (RPSs) adopted
               by neighboring states.

               While conservation groups laud the advent of renewable, emission-free energy, there
               also is concern regarding the potential adverse impacts to habitats and species that
               could result from utility-scale wind energy development. This document seeks to
               facilitate efforts to identify, evaluate and avoid potential adverse impacts on wildlife and
               wildlife habitats that could accompany utility-scale wind energy development. Through
               this project, the Virginia Wind Energy Collaborative and its environmental working group
               sought to assist the emerging wind energy industry by offering an environmental
               screening tool to be used during the initial macro-siting process.








                                                             - 2 -

 = Page 3 =







                                                                            S
                                                                                           V
                                                        C
                                          L
               I NTRODUCTION TO THE  ANDSCAPE  LASSIFICATION  YSTEM FOR  IRGINIA
               The Landscape Classification System for Virginia was developed to facilitate the
               inclusion of environmental factors into the macro-site selection process. In conjunction
                                                       1
               with the Virginia Wind Resource Map , the Landscape Classification System for Virginia
               is intended to be of use to wind developers, state and federal agencies, landowners,
               and environmental organizations involved in siting of utility-scale wind development in
               Virginia and to increase awareness of real and potential adverse environmental impacts
                                      2
               for areas with Class 3  and above wind resources.
               The Landscape Classification System is comprised of three categories overlaid on a
               base layer of Class 3 and above wind resources derived from the AWS TrueWind
               Solutions “Wind Resource Map of Virginia.” Analyses consider sites with Class 3 or
               better wind resources, given that current or imminent technologies can exploit wind
               energy resources economically at, but not below, this level. Figure 1 depicts the
               distribution of the Class 3 and higher wind energy resources in Virginia.

               The three landscape categories are characterized by the potential for conflict in a given
               area between utility-scale wind powered energy generation facilities and other existing
               or potential uses. The categories are:
                     Unsuitable: Mapped

                      Flagged for Potential Use Conflict
                     Unclassified

               There was broad consensus reached between members of the Virginia Wind Energy
               Collaborative and members of the working group with the respect to the definition of
               these landscape categories and the assignment of data layers to them.

               A fourth category labeled    Unsuitable: Unmapped     was defined by the working group to
               include areas of unknown geographic extent that are unsuitable for wind energy
               development due to adverse biological impacts.        These are areas that host avian and
               bat activity. This category carries significance, as defined, only with respect to the
               notion that there are potential impacts that would be better understood were the
               relevant GIS data available. In addition, the spirit of this document resides within the
               categories for which such data do exist. The           Unsuitable: Unmapped      category is
               therefore not included within the Landscape Classification System for Virginia since
               mapping information, by definition, is not available. However, it is the recommendation
               of VWEC that developers should seek to avoid and mitigate any potential adverse
               impacts on the groups designated for assignment to this land classification.



               1  Michael Brower.  2002.  Wind Resource Maps of Virginia.  Prepared for Commonwealth of Virginia, Department of Mines, Minerals,
               and Energy, Division of Energy (Contract #C026047) and US Department of Energy, Philadelphia Regional Office (Order #DE-
               AP43-01R3-25005-00) by TrueWind Solutions, LLC.
               2  The potential for an area to generate electricity from the wind is categorized according to Wind Power Class.  Each class
                                                             2
               represents a range of mean wind power density (in units of W/m ) or equivalent mean wind speed at the specified height(s) above
               ground. A Class 1 wind resource area has very light winds; higher Class numbers indicate stronger winds - Class 7 is the highest
               wind power class.  Areas designated Class 3 or greater are suitable for most wind turbine applications.  See:
               http://rredc.nrel.gov/wind/pubs/atlas/chp1.html .


                                                             - 3 -

 = Page 4 =


































                        Figure 1: Distribution of Class 3 and Higher Wind Energy Resources in Virginia.
               Each Landscape category includes a number of land use types compiled from various
               sources. These types include public lands; private nature reserves; known occurrences
               of rare, threatened, and endangered species; significant natural features and important
               scenic and recreation areas. Table 1 provides an overview of land use/management
               types included in each Landscape Class, as well as a brief description of the potential
               use conflict that could result from utility-scale wind energy development in each land
               use type. Definitions of land use types and descriptions of potential environmental
               impacts are detailed below.

               Three general categories of potential use conflict were identified, these are:
                      Legal/Regulatory Use Conflict: Utility-scale wind development is inconsistent with
                       the permitted use of a site as established in law, regulation, management
                       prescription, or deed.
                      Environmental Use Conflict: Utility-scale wind development is likely to change the
                       physical structure and chemical properties of a site such that a permanent shift in
                       desired biological composition will result.
                      Aesthetic Use Conflict: Utility-scale wind development may effect a change in the
                       physical appearance and user experience of a site beyond stated management
                       objectives.

               The examination of potential adverse impacts is not intended to be exhaustive or
               authoritative. Impacts examined for this project were limited to those that have been
               linked to utility-scale wind energy development in the Mid-Atlantic or other regions. The
               working group acknowledged that all parties may not agree on the significance of some
               of the impacts addressed here. At the same time, well-informed decision making can
               best be assured by acknowledging impacts attributed to wind energy development that
               have proven controversial in the past.

               The data sets incorporated in this project are the best available at time of distribution,
               and represent the state of knowledge at the time that this project was completed. Users


                                                             - 4 -

 = Page 5 =







               of this product should consult with relevant agencies during their site-scoping process to
               ensure that decisions are made on the basis of the most current information. Contact
               information for updated data may be found in Appendix 1.


                              Table 1: Summary of Landscape Classification System for Virginia.
                Conflict Significance    Land use/Management Type                       Potential Use
                        Class                                                           Conflict
               Unsuitable: Mapped        National Park Service – Appalachian National   Legal/Regulatory
                                         Scenic Trail and 5-mile buffer zone
                                         National Park Service – Blue Ridge Parkway     Legal/Regulatory
                                         National Park Service – All of Shenandoah      Legal/Regulatory
                                         National Park (SNP), including: Skyline Drive,
                                         the Skyline Drive Historic District, the
                                         Appalachian National Scenic Trail within SNP
                                         and the Shenandoah Wilderness Areas within
                                         SNP

                                         U.S. Forest Service – Wilderness Areas         Legal/Regulatory
                                         U.S. Forest Service – National Scenic Areas    Legal/Regulatory
                                         U.S. Forest Service – Special Biologic Areas &  Legal/Regulatory
                                         SIA – Shenandoah Mountain Crest
                                         U.S. Forest Service – Inventoried Roadless     Legal/Regulatory
                                         Areas
                                         U.S. Forest Service – Research Natural Areas  Legal/Regulatory

                                         U.S. Forest Service – Wilderness Study Areas  Legal/Regulatory
                                         U.S. Forest Service – Inventoried Old-Growth   Environmental
                                         Forest (Jefferson National Forest)
                                         Virginia Department of Conservation and        Legal/Regulatory
                                         Recreation, Division of Natural Heritage –
                                         State Parks and Natural Area Preserves

                                         Virginia Outdoor Foundation (VOF)              Legal/Regulatory
                                         Easements

                                         U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service National Wildlife  Legal/Regulatory
                                         Refuges

                                         The Nature Conservancy Preserves               Environmental
                Submerged Aquatic Vegetation Environmental
               Flagged for Potential     National Park Service – Appalachian National   Aesthetic
               Use Conflict              Scenic Trail and 5 to 10-mile buffer zone
                                         The Nature Conservancy Ecoregional Portfolio  Environmental
                                         Sites






                                                             - 5 -

 = Page 6 =









                                         Virginia Department of Conservation and        Environmental
                                         Recreation, Division of Natural Heritage –
                                         Heritage Sites
                                         U.S. Forest Service – Candidate Wilderness     Environmental
                                         Areas
                                         U.S. Forest Service – Uninventoried Roadless  Environmental
                                         Areas
                                         U.S. Forest Service – Remaining National       Legal/Regulatory
                                         Forest Lands
                                         Virginia Department of Game and Inland         Environmental,
                                         Fisheries Wildlife Management Areas            Aesthetic
                                         Virginia Department of Forestry State Forests   Environmental

                                         Cold Water Streams                             Environmental
               Unknown                   Areas of Unknown Suitability
               Significance
                                         Wind Energy Potential Class 2 or Less



                                                                 V
                                                  S
               L ANDSCAPE  LASSIFICATION  YSTEM FOR  IRGINIA
                              C
               U NSUITABLE      APPED
                            : M
               The category “Unsuitable Mapped” is defined for areas of known geographic extent that
               are unsuitable for utility-scale wind development due to a direct conflict with legal or
               administrative mandates regarding the management of the site, and adverse impacts to
               irreplaceable biological resources. The following land use/management types are
               included in this class.
               National Park Service – Appalachian National Scenic Trail and 5-mile buffer zone

                   The Constitution of the Appalachian Trail Conference (ATC) states that one of the
                   purposes of the ATC is “to preserve and restore the natural environment of the Trail
                   and its adjacent lands.” In order to provide trail users with a wilderness experience,
                   the ATC uses buffer zone on each side of the Appalachian Trail to assess potential
                   interference with the Trail’s viewshed from powerplant, commercial, wind farm,
                   transportation and other forms of development. The ATC advocates for no
                   construction of utility-scale wind energy development within 0 to 5 miles on either
                   side of the Trail, and requests that developers considering a development in this
                   zone contact the ATC as early as possible in the site scoping process.
                   GIS Users Note   : In order for the path of the Appalachian Trail (AT) to be visible on
                   printed maps, the thickness of the line representing the AT has been enlarged well
                   beyond the 5 or 10 mile buffer. An accurate calculation of the buffer is easily
                   achieved when using the digital data included in this project.




                                                             - 6 -

 = Page 7 =







               National Park Service – Blue Ridge Parkway

                   The Blue Ridge Parkway follows the high crests of the central and southern
                   Appalachians for 469 miles from Shenandoah National Park in Virginia to the Great
                   Smoky Mountains National Park in North Carolina, traversing an unsurpassed
                   diversity of climate zones, vegetation zones, physiographic zones, and geological
                   features. The more than 92,000 acres of Parkway lands pass through a highland
                   area of five degrees longitude and approximately 3 degrees latitude, making it the
                   third largest unit of the National Park Service in terms of area covered. Park
                   resources include 400 streams (150 headwaters), and 47 Natural Heritage Areas
                   (areas set aside as national, regional or state examples of exemplary natural
                                  3
                   communities).  The fundamental purpose of the national parks “… is to conserve the
                   scenery and the natural and historic objects and wildlife therein and to provide for
                   the enjoyment of the same in such a manner and by such means as will leave them
                                                                           4
                   unimpaired for the enjoyment of future generations.”  The NPS does have authority
                   to grant Rights-of-Way across BRP lands, subject to NEPA, NPS Management
                                                                                5
                   Policies and Guidelines, and other legislative protections.
               National Park Service – Shenandoah National Park (SNP)

                   This land use type encompasses the entire Park, which can not allow commercial
                   development except for the provision of visitor services. The Park includes many
                   special features incompatible with utility-scale wind energy development, including
                   Skyline Drive, the Skyline Drive Historic District, the Appalachian National Scenic
                   Trail within SNP and the Shenandoah Wilderness Areas within SNP. The
                   Congressionally-designated    Shenandoah Wilderness       within SNP is the largest such
                   area in the mid-Atlantic states.

               U.S. Forest Service – Wilderness Areas
                   A Wilderness Area is a tract of “undeveloped Federal land retaining its primeval
                   character and influence, without permanent improvements or human habitation,
                                                                                                            6
                   which is protected and managed so as to preserve its natural conditions.”
                   Wilderness Areas are established only by an Act of Congress and are managed by
                   the Federal agency on whose lands they are located (National Park Service, Forest
                   Service, Bureau of Land Management, or Fish and Wildlife Service). Management
                   directions are established by the agency, but resource extraction, permanent
                   structures, roads, and mechanical transport are explicitly prohibited by the
                   Wilderness Act of 1964.  Wilderness Areas together form the National Wilderness
                   Preservation System.






               3
                 National Park Service, Blue Ridge Parkway Home Page.   http://www.nps.gov/blri/ .  Accessed August 22, 2004.
               4
                 National Park Service Organic Act 16 U.S.C. 1, 1916.
               5  Molling, Suzette, D. Anderson, A. Hess.  August 1, 2003.  “Blue Ridge Parkway Environmental Assessment Guide for Right-of-
               Ways.”  Division of Resource Planning and Professional Services, Blue Ridge Parkway.  Viewed August 22, 2004, at:
               http://data2.itc.nps.gov/parks/blri/ppdocuments/EA%20Info%20Guide%20for%20ROWs-08-03.pdf.
               6
                 Wilderness Act of 1964.

                                                             - 7 -

 = Page 8 =







               U.S. Forest Service  National Scenic Areas
                                      –
                   Located in Amherst County, Virginia, the 7,580 acre Mount Pleasant National Scenic
                   Area was created by an Act of Congress in 1994. The National Scenic Area
                   designation is for the protection of the watershed and scenic values, recreation use,
                   protection of wildlife and their habitat, and for other purposes. As stated in the Mount
                   Pleasant National Scenic Area Act, the purpose of conveying this status onto the
                   Mount Pleasant area was to:

                   •    ensure appropriate protection and preservation of the scenic quality, water
                       quality, natural characteristics, and water resources;

                   •    protect and manage vegetation to provide wildlife and fish habitat, consistent with
                       protection and preservation of resources identified above;

                   •    provide areas that may develop characteristics of old-growth forests; and

                   •    provide a variety of recreation opportunities that are not inconsistent with the
                                                  7
                       purposes set forth above.

               U.S. Forest Service – Special Biologic Areas (SBAs)
                   SBAs are one of four categories of Special Interest Areas (SIA's) identified on
                   National Forest Lands. The other categories are SIA - Geologic, SIA - Historic, and
                   SIA - Shenandoah Mountain Crest.  Only SBA’s (also known as SIA-Biologic) & the
                   SIA – Shenandoah Mountain Crest are included in this screening tool.

                   The Forest Service designates these SIA's during Forest Plan revisions. SBAs,
                   include lands that support key components and concentrations of the Forest's
                   biological diversity. These areas typically include high quality natural communities
                   such as high elevation mountain tops, shale barrens, caves and karst features,
                   wetlands, and habitat for threatened, endangered, and sensitive species. Thirty-eight
                                                                    8
                   SIA’s - Biologic are designated on the GWNF.
                   The Special Interest Area for   Shenandoah Mountain Crest       extends from Cow Knob
                   south to Little Bald Knob. This 43,000 acre area extends special protections under

                   the George Washington National Forest Plan for the variety of threatened,
                   endangered, and sensitive species and unique natural communities, including at
                   least 15 species of plants and 13 species of animals plus their associated habitats.
                   The Revised Land & Resource Management Plan for the            Jefferson National Forest
                   utilizes different management terminology from the George Washington Plan,
                   referring to management prescriptions rather than areas. Several of these
                   prescriptions are similar to SBAs, including Botanical-Zoological Areas (4,700
                   acres), Rare Communities (7,400 acres) and Habitat Conservation Areas for the
                   Peaks of Otter salamander (varying acreages). In addition, the Jefferson Plan
                   designates protected areas surrounding hibernacula of the federally-endangered

               7  U.S. Senate Bill 2142.” Mount Pleasant National Scenic Area Act” 1994  viewed at: http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-
               bin/query/z?c103:S.2142.IS:
               8  USDA Forest Service.  1993.   Final Revised Land and Resource Management Plan, George Washington National Forest . pp.  3-
               107 through 3-114. Available at: http://www.southernregion.fs.fed.us/gwj/forestplan/gwplandocs/gw_forestplan.pdf.


                                                             - 8 -

 = Page 9 =







                   Indiana Bat Primary Cave Protection Areas (900 acres), and Secondary Cave
                   Protection Areas (8,800 acres). The Jefferson Plan also designates a variety of
                   additional Special Areas. "The Forest Service is committed to protect… areas with
                   scenic, historical, geological, botanical, zoological, paleontological or other special
                   characteristics, and classify areas that possess unusual recreation and scientific
                   values…" The following are designated Special Areas – Hoop Hole (4,400 acres),
                   Whitetop Mountain (5,100 acres), Mt. Rogers Crest Zone (5,100 acres), North Creek
                   (5,200 acre), Whitetop Laurel (4,200 acres), North Fork of Pound (5,500 acres).     9,12

                   GIS Users Note:    These areas are not reflected in the Unsuitable coverage due to
                   capacity limitations at this stage of the project, but are included in the National
                                                                  10
                   Forest Lands layer in the Flagged Category.
               U.S. Forest Service – Inventoried Roadless Areas (IRAs)
                   Inventoried Roadless Areas are undeveloped tracts of National Forest land “that met
                   the minimum criteria for wilderness designation under the Wilderness Act and that
                   [were] inventoried during the Forest Service’s Roadless Area Review and Evaluation
                   (RARE II) process, subsequent assessments, or forest planning. These areas were
                   granted special protections under a formal rule making process initiated at the
                                                             11
                   request of the Clinton Administration.  The Final “Roadless Area Conservation
                                                                                 12
                   Rule” published in the Federal Register Jan. 12, 2001  prohibits - with certain
                   limited exceptions - new road construction and reconstruction in inventoried roadless
                   areas on National Forest System lands, and prohibits cutting, sale, and removal of
                                                             13
                   timber in inventoried roadless areas.  These areas are published as a set of
                   inventoried roadless area maps included in the          Forest Service Roadless Area
                   Conservation, Final Environmental Impact Statement,        Volume 2, dated November
                         14
                   2000.  These areas are also described in Appendix C to both the 1993 George
                                                                             15
                   Washington and 2004 Jefferson management plans.  At time of press, the Bush
                   administration had proposed a modification to the 2001 Roadless Area Conservation
                   Rule that would require governors to petition the Forest Service to have roadless

                   areas in their states protected from logging, road-building and other industrial
                   activities. IRA’s will remain in the unsuitable category, regardless of whether the
                   Bush Administration modifies the rule.




               9  USDA Forest Service.  2004.   Revised Land and Resource Management Plan, Jefferson National Forest . Chapter 3.  Available at:
               http://www.southernregion.fs.fed.us/gwj/forestplan/plan.pdf.
               10  USDA Forest Service.  2003.   Draft Proposed Revised Land and Resource Management Plan, Jefferson National Forest .
               Chapter 3.
               11  Federal Register: October 19, 1999 ”Action: Notice of intent to prepare an environmental impact statement”. (Volume 64, Number
               201), Notices. Page 56306-56307.  From the Federal Register Online via GPO Access [wais.access.gpo.gov].  [DOCID:fr19oc99-
               27]. Available at: http://www.roadless.fs.fed.us/documents/noi.htm.
               12  Federal Register, January 12, 2001. Department of Agriculture Forest Service. Special Areas; Roadless Area Conservation; Final
               Rule36 CFR Part 294. Page 3244.
               13  USDA Forest Service Webpage.  Roadless Area Conservation. Final Rule.
               http://www.roadless.fs.fed.us/documents/rule/index.shtml . Modified January 16, 2001. viewed September 13, 2004.
               14
                 Forest Service Roadless Area Conservation, Final EIS, Volume 1.
               15
                  USDA Forest Service.  2004.  Revised Land and Resource Management Plan, Jefferson National Forest.

                                                             - 9 -

 = Page 10 =







               U.S. Forest Service – Research Natural Areas (RNAs)

                   RNA’s are part of a national network of ecological resources designated for
                   research, education and maintenance of biological diversity on National Forest
                   System lands. The existence of unique examples of natural communities and the
                   biological diversity they support are the main reasons for designating an RNA.
                   Research Natural Areas (RNA's) are designated by the Chief of the Forest Service
                                                                                                   16
                   following a formal study and recommendation by the Regional Forester.  On the
                   George Washington National Forest, Little Laurel Run (2,000 acres) was designated
                   a Research Natural Area in the 1930s. Six additional areas on the George
                   Washington National Forest are identified as candidates for possible RNA
                   designation: Big Levels, Laurel Run, Maple Flats, Shale Barren-Complex, Skidmore,
                   and Slabcamp/Bearwallow. There are currently no RNAs on the Jefferson National
                   Forest, however the plan designates several areas that are similar to RNA’s in their
                   management prescription. These areas are included in the coverage of National
                   Forest Lands listed in the Flagged category.
               U.S. Forest Service – Wilderness Study Areas

                   A Wilderness Study Area is a tract of undeveloped Federal land administered “so as
                   to maintain [its] presently existing wilderness character and potential for inclusion in
                                                                      17
                   the National Wilderness Preservation System.”  Wilderness Study Areas may be
                   designated by an Act of Congress by the Chief of the Forest Service, or by
                   recommendation in the Land and Resource Management Plan for each national
                          18
                   forest.
               U.S. Forest Service – Inventoried Old Growth Forest
                   In 1997, the U.S. Forest Service published its “Guidance for Conserving and
                   Restoring Old-Growth Forest Communities on National Forests in the Southern
                            19
                   Region.”   The introduction to this guidance states:
                       “The U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Southern Region,
                       recognizes old-growth forests as a valuable natural resource worthy of
                       protection, restoration, and management. Old-growth forests provide a
                       variety of values, such as biological diversity, wildlife habitat, recreation,
                       esthetics, soil productivity, water quality, aquatic habitat, cultural values,
                       and high-value timber products. Old-growth communities are rare or
                       largely absent in the southeastern forests of the United States. … For
                       these reasons the national forests are making efforts to address the
                       restoration of this missing portion of the southern forest ecosystems. …
                       current Federal laws and regulations associated with the management of
                       national forests do not specifically mandate old-growth management.

               16
                  Virginia's National Forests are part of the Southern Region (Region 8) headquartered in Atlanta.
               17
                  Final Environmental Impact Statement, Land and Resource Management Plan, Jefferson National Forest, 1985.
               18  USDA Forest Service.  2004.   Final Environmental Impact Statement for the Revised Land and Resource Management Plan,
               Jefferson National Forest ..
               19  USDA Forest Service. 1997. “Guidance for Conserving and Restoring Old-Growth Forest Communities on National Forests in the
               Southern Region”.  Available at: http://www.southernregion.fs.fed.us/resources/documents/R8-Old-Growth-Report.pdf


                                                            - 10 -

 = Page 11 =







                       These various laws do, however, provide direction to the Forest Service in
                       such areas as the management of multiple natural resources and values,
                       the protection and recovery of federally listed threatened and endangered
                       species and their habitats, providing habitats to sustain viable populations
                       of vertebrate species, and maintaining and enhancing the diversity of plant
                       and animal communities that would be expected in a natural forest.”
                   The old growth forest layer included in the screening tool is from the Jefferson
                   National Forest (JNF). The JNF began an inventory of old growth in 1989, later
                   incorporating the guidelines for defining eastern old growth cited above. The
                   Jefferson FEIS explains that additional old-growth areas are likely to be found during
                   the implementation of the Forest Plan. Current mapping shows 49,993 acres of old
                   growth on the Jefferson in small- (1-99 acres) and medium- (100-2,499) sized
                            20
                   patches.   Inventory and mapping of old growth on the George Washington National
                   Forest will occur when that Forest’s Land and Resource Management Plan is
                   revised, within the next few years.
                   GIS Users Note:    It is recommended for the purposes of environmental screening
                   that in addition to protecting the area of defined old growth, some buffer zone also
                   be retained around old-growth areas.
               Virginia Department of Conservation and Recreation, Division of Natural Heritage
               – State Parks and Natural Area Preserves
                   Virginia's State Park system was initiated on June 15, 1936, when the first six parks
                   in the system opened. There are now 34 State Parks spread across the
                   Commonwealth. Virginia's State Parks were recently judged the best in the nation by
                   the National Sporting Goods Association's Sports Foundation Inc. Virginia voters in
                   2002 approved a bond referendum to improve and repair State Park facilities and
                   acquire additional park land. The Natural Area Preserve System protects examples
                   of some of the rarest natural communities and rare species habitats in Virginia. A
                   site becomes a component of the preserve system once it is dedicated as a natural
                   area preserve by the Director of the Department of Conservation & Recreation. Most
                   of the preserves are owned by the Department of Conservation and Recreation, but
                   some are owned by local governments, universities, private citizens, and private
                   conservation organizations. These areas are managed for the conservation of
                   biodiversity, and only activities compatible with that purpose are permitted on those
                   lands.
               Virginia Outdoor Foundation (VOF) Easements

                   The Virginia Outdoors Foundation (VOF) is the state agency charged with
                   preserving the scenic and natural resources of the Commonwealth. VOF holds
                   conservation easements on nearly 250,000 acres of open space lands throughout
                   the state. Some of these properties are located in areas with levels of wind energy
                   appropriate for utility-scale wind power development.  However, all of the easements
                   currently held by VOF prohibit construction of commercial and utility-scale wind



               20
                  Ibid. p 3-116.

                                                            - 11 -

 = Page 12 =







                   turbines. VOF does not anticipate a policy change that would allow large-scale
                   commercial windmills to be permitted on VOF-eased lands. VOF does hold several
                   easements that permit small-scale windmills on specific properties. Examples of
                   acceptable uses include windmills that may be used to generate electricity or water
                   sources for agricultural activities or domestic consumption.
                   VWEC is in receipt of a letter from the VOF recommending that VOF-held
                   easements be classified “Unsuitable.”

               U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service National Wildlife Refuges
                   The National Wildlife Refuge (NWR) System is managed by the Fish and Wildlife
                   Service within the U.S. Department of the Interior. The mission of the National
                   Wildlife Refuge System is to work with others, to conserve, protect and enhance fish,
                   wildlife, and plants and their habitats for the continuing benefit of the American
                   people.  Virginia has 14 NWRs, located mostly along the coast or major rivers. Many
                   of these NWRs were established to protect endangered species, including the bald
                   eagle and other bird species and several sea turtle species. The National Wildlife
                   Refuge System Improvement Act of 1997 gave refuges, formerly managed as
                   isolated islands of habitat, an overarching mission and mandated the implementation
                   of an ecosystem-based approach to wildlife conservation. As federal lands, any
                   developments on USFWS holdings are subject to NEPA.

               The Nature Conservancy Preserves
                   The Mission of The Nature Conservancy is to preserve the plants, animals and
                   natural communities that represent the diversity of life on Earth by protecting the
                                                               21
                   lands and waters they need to survive.  TNC owns and/or manages only those
                   lands and waters that are critical to the success of its mission, and seeks to manage
                   all of its conservation properties to promote the long-term survival of vulnerable
                   native species and native community types. TNC will not knowingly engage in any
                   practice or use that is inconsistent with this goal. TNC may engage in compatible
                   human use at conservation sites when the use is designed to meet programmatic
                   goals after development of a documented hypothesis establishing the programmatic
                   benefit, and when the use will not generate collateral threats to conservation targets,
                   and provided that the use is consistent with Conservancy values. Contemplation of a
                   programmatic human or economic use must be approved by the Regional Director.
                   TNC in Virginia has determined that utility-scale wind energy development is not a
                                                                         22
                   compatible use of its preserves or managed areas.
               Submerged Aquatic Vegetation

                   The Virginia Institute of Marine Science identifies submerged aquatic vegetation
                   (SAV) is a diverse assembly of rooted macrophytes found in shoal areas of





               21  The Nature Conservancy Homepage, How We Work.  2003. Viewed on TNC Intranet Policy and Procedures WebPages Dec. 4,
               2003. http://nature.org/aboutus/howwework/.
               22  The Nature Conservancy, Policy and Procedures Manual.  2003.  p.p. 3, 7.  Viewed on TNC Intranet Policy and Procedures
               webpage Dec. 4, 2003.


                                                            - 12 -

 = Page 13 =







                                     23
                   Chesapeake Bay , including many high resource wind areas in Virginia. Historically
                                                                                        24
                   SAV contributed to the high productivity of Chesapeake Bay , but a dramatic
                                                                                           25
                   decline of all SAV species was noted in the late 1960s and 1970s.  In response to
                   the loss of a critical component of the Bay Ecosystem, the 1987 Chesapeake Bay
                   Agreement, was signed by the governors of Pennsylvania, Maryland, and Virginia,
                   the mayor of the District of Columbia, the chair of the Chesapeake Bay Commission,
                   and the administrator of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency. This Agreement
                   set as a major commitment the "need to determine the essential elements of habitat
                   quality and environmental quality necessary to support living resources and to see
                                                                               26
                   that these conditions are attained and maintained"  (Chesapeake Executive
                   Council, 1987). The   Submerged Aquatic Vegetation Policy for the Chesapeake Bay
                   and Tidal Tributaries     27  (Chesapeake Executive Council, 1989) and the
                   Implementation Plan for the Submerged Aquatic Vegetation Policy (Chesapeake
                   Executive Council, 1990) were developed to guide managers and scientists in areas
                   of SAV assessment, protection, education, and research.


                                          U
                              P
                                              C
               F LAGGED FOR  OTENTIAL  SE  ONFLICT
               This category includes those areas known to support sensitive biological or recreational
               resources or those areas necessitating formal or legal Administrative Review by a
               managing agency.

               National Park Service – Appalachian National Scenic Trail and 5 to 10-mile buffer
               zone

                   In order to provide trail users with a wilderness experience, the ATC uses five- and
                   ten-mile buffer zones on each side of the Appalachian Trail to alleviate potential
                   interference with the Trail’s viewshed from powerplant, commercial, wind farm,
                   transportation and other forms of development. The ATC requests that any
                   developer interested in such areas consult with the ATC regarding viewshed
                   interference in the earliest stages of potential wind farm siting.
                   GIS Users Note   : In order for the path of the Appalachian Trail (AT) to be visible on
                   printed maps, the thickness of the line representing the AT has been enlarged well
                   beyond the 5 or 10 mile buffer. An accurate calculation of the buffer is easily
                   achieved when using the digital data included in this project.


               23  VIMS SAV Mapping Lab. VIMS SAV Web Page [Internet].  Updated Oct. 6, 2003.  Viewed Dec. 9, 2003.  Available at:
               http://www.vims.edu/bio/sav/.
               24  Kemp, et al., 1984 Cited on VIMS SAV Web Page [Internet] “Submerged Aquatic Vegetation (SAV) Species in Chesapeake Bay”.
               Updated Oct. 17, 1996. Available at: http://www.vims.edu/bio/sav/aboutsav.html.
               25  Orth, R. J. and K. A. Moore. 1983. “Chesapeake Bay: An Unprecedented Decline in Submerged Aquatic Vegetation.”  Science .
               222:51-53. Cited on VIMS SAV Web Page [Internet] “Submerged Aquatic Vegetation (SAV) Species in Chesapeake Bay”. Updated
               Oct. 17, 1996. Available at: http://www.vims.edu/bio/sav/aboutsav.html.
               26  Chesapeake Executive Council. 1989. Cited on VIMS SAV Web Page [Internet] “Submerged Aquatic Vegetation (SAV) Species in
               Chesapeake Bay”. Updated Oct. 17, 1996. Available at: http://www.vims.edu/bio/sav/aboutsav.html.
               27  Chesapeake Executive Council. 1989. “Submerged Aquatic Vegetation Policy for the Chesapeake Bay and Tidal Tributaries”.
               Annapolis, MD. July. Cited on VIMS SAV Web Page [Internet] “Submerged Aquatic Vegetation (SAV) Species in Chesapeake Bay”.
               Updated Oct. 17, 1996. Available at: http://www.vims.edu/bio/sav/aboutsav.html.


                                                            - 13 -

 = Page 14 =







               The Nature Conservancy Ecoregional Portfolio Sites

                   Ecoregions are large areas of land or water defined by their distinct climate, geology
                   and native species. Because ecoregions are defined by the same variables that
                   govern the distribution of organisms, they provide an effective unit for regional
                   conservation planning. An ecoregional portfolio is the minimum set of sites (on public
                   or private land) that, if managed appropriately, will ensure the long-term survival of
                   all native biodiversity within that ecoregion. Numeric goals are set for the minimum
                   number of occurrences needed to sustain viable populations of each targeted native
                   plant, animal and natural community, for the next 100 years. Finally, sites known to
                   support the best remaining examples of targeted plants, animals, and natural
                   communities are selected to form the portfolio. Since the selected sites represent
                   only the minimum number needed to meet viability goals, the loss of any site
                   undermines the integrity of the entire portfolio.

               Virginia Department of Conservation and Recreation, Division of Natural Heritage
                                 †
               – Heritage Sites
                   The DNH Screening Coverage includes those areas of the landscape that contribute
                   to the conservation of Natural Heritage Resources. These resources are defined in
                   the Virginia Natural Area Preserves Act of 1989 (Section 10.1-209 through 217,
                   Code of Virginia), as "the habitat of rare, threatened, and endangered plant and
                   animal species; exemplary natural communities, habitats, and ecosystems; and
                   other natural features of the Commonwealth". DCR-DNH maintains lists of  Natural
                   Heritage Resources and revises them as new data become available. Taxa are
                   added to the list when it is determined that their continued existence in Virginia is in
                                                                                    28
                   jeopardy, and deleted when data indicate they are secure.  The DNH Screening
                   Coverage can be used to identify conflicts with development activities, and for
                   proactive planning to ensure that development projects successfully avoid or
                   enhance Natural Heritage resources.    29

               U.S. Forest Service –Candidate Wilderness Areas

                   The Working Group has classified these lands Flagged until such time as the U.S.
                   Congress passes S. 2342, H.R. 4202, or successor legislation. Should either bill
                   become law, these lands will be placed in the unsuitable category.

                   On April 22, 2004, Sen. John Warner (R-VA) and Congressman Rick Boucher (D-
                   VA) introduced the   Virginia Ridge and Valley Wilderness and National Scenic Area
                   Act of 2004 (S. 2342/H.R. 4202)    . The legislation would create four new Wilderness
                   Areas, expand five existing Wilderness areas and designate two National Scenic
                   Areas in Virginia’s Jefferson National Forest. In total, the measure will provide
                   lasting protection for some 40,000 acres in portions of Craig, Grayson, Giles, Lee,
                   Montgomery and Smyth counties. Each of the new Wilderness and National Scenic



               †  The GIS data pertaining to this category are temporarily withheld while license agreements are negotiated.
               28  Virginia Department of Conservation and Recreation, Division of Natural Heritage.  An Overview of the Natural Heritage Program
               http://www.dcr.state.va.us/dnh/mission.htm  viewed 12/4/03.
               29
                  VDCR-DNH.  2003.  Metadata accompanying DNH Screening Layer.

                                                            - 14 -

 = Page 15 =







                   Area designations has been endorsed by either the U.S. Forest Service or the Board
                   of Supervisors of the county in which the area is located.
                   The proposed new Wilderness Areas are:

                   1)  Stone Mountain- Lee County.
                   2)  Raccoon Branch- Smyth County.
                   3) Brush Mountain- Montgomery County.
                   4)  Brush Mountain East- Craig County.

                   The proposed new National Scenic Areas are:

                   1)  Crawfish Valley- Smyth County.
                   2)  Seng Mountain- Smyth County.

               U.S. Forest Service – Uninventoried Roadless Areas

                   A Geographic Information Systems based analysis was conducted by Bruce and
                                   30
                   Giecek (2003)  to determine the location of large roadless parcels in both the
                   Jefferson and George Washington National Forests. The most recent Forest Service
                   data representing roads and Forest Service land ownership was evaluated to locate
                   parcels that are: 1) Greater than 1000 acres and adjacent to existing Wilderness or
                   Inventoried Roadless Areas (IRA), or 2) Greater than 5000 acres and not adjacent to
                   existing Wilderness and Inventoried Roadless Areas. The 1000 and 5000 acre
                   criteria were also used to guide the Forest Service's more recent mapping of
                   Uninventoried Roadless Areas for the Clinton administration's Roadless Area
                                        31
                   Conservation Rule.  However, this GIS based analysis yields significant acreage
                   that was not included in the IRA-RARE II analysis. Considered together, Wilderness
                   areas, Wilderness study areas, IRAs, and URAs represent a significant portion of the
                   roadless lands in Virginia's National Forests.

               U.S. Forest Service – Remaining National Forest Lands
                   National Forest lands are managed by the U.S. Forest Service within the
                   Department of Agriculture. As set forth in law, the mission of the USDA Forest
                   Service is to sustain the health, diversity, and productivity of the Nation’s forests and
                                                                                       32
                   grasslands to meet the needs of present and future generations.
                   The two National Forests in Virginia are the George Washington (GWNF) and
                   Jefferson (JNF), established in 1917 and 1936 respectively. Together, these Forests
                                                                                                           33
                   total about 1.7 million acres including some lands in Kentucky and West Virginia,
                                                                                                      34
                   and are the primary provider of dispersed recreation opportunities in Virginia.  The

               30  Bruce, Chris. GIS Analyst, The Nature Conservancy. Charlottesville, VA and Don Giecek.  Virginia Wilderness Committee.
               31  Federal Register: October 19, 1999 (Volume 64, Number 201).  Page 56306-56307. DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE Forest
               Service - National Forest System Roadless Areas, ACTION: Notice of intent to prepare an environmental impact statement.
               32  USDA Forest Service  http://www.fs.fed.us/aboutus/mission.shtml  Last Modified: Wednesday, Jun 05, 2002 at 04:04 PM EDT.
               Viewed 12/4/03.
               33  USDA Forest Service - George Washington and Jefferson National Forests.   http://www.southernregion.fs.fed.us/gwj/nfhistory.htm
               Viewed 12/5/03.
               34  DCR's Virginia Outdoors Plan 2002, p. 108.


                                                            - 15 -

 = Page 16 =







                   George Washington and Jefferson National Forests are each governed by their own
                   Land and Resource Management Plan (LRMP), which defines a variety of
                   management "prescriptions" (Jefferson) or "areas" (GW), with guidelines for what
                   management activities are allowed. The current Forest Plans for Virginia’s two
                   National Forest differ greatly in their format, and the current plan for the Jefferson
                   was published in early 2004 spring. Because of this, users are advised that a
                   detailed analysis of the Jefferson prescriptions was not possible, and many areas
                   that may be classified as unsuitable have yet to be delineated.

                   At time of distribution, potential wind energy development on National Forests is
                   guided by BLM Instruction Memorandum No. 2003-020, Interim Wind Energy
                                        35
                   Development Policy .
               Virginia Department of Game and Inland Fisheries Wildlife Management Areas
                   There are currently 29 Wildlife Management Areas (WMAs) managed by Virginia
                   Department of Game and Inland Fisheries, totaling about 180,000 acres. WMAs are
                   managed for public hunting of game animals, the provision of non-game wildlife
                                                                                       36
                   habitat, and passive recreation such as hiking and birdwatching.
               Virginia Department of Forestry State Forests
                   The Virginia Department of Forestry (VDOF) manages 16 State Forests and other
                   state lands totaling about 50,000 acres. Since its inception, the State Forests have
                   been charged with managing the forestland to ensure a sustained yield of timber for
                   the operation and maintenance of the resource and stability of the local economy
                   while at the same time fulfilling multiple benefits, such as timber management,
                   recreation, aesthetics, wildlife, natural reserves and water quality. Special
                   Management Areas provide demonstration and research areas for the promotion of
                                                                                   37
                   good forestry practices and observation of applied research.  At time of distribution,
                   the intersection between VA State Forests and developable wind energy resources
                   was minimal; however, additions to the State Forest System expected to occur in the
                   next few years are likely to increase potential for use conflict.

                                      †
               Cold Water Streams
                   Virginia’s cold water streams provide habitat for the indigenous brook trout
                   ( Salvelinus fontinalis ), as well as introduced rainbow trout ( Oncorhynchus mykiss     )
                   and brown trout ( Salmo trutta ). These streams are primarily associated with forested
                   mountain ridges, which also represent the inland areas of greatest wind energy
                   development potential. The trout species and other aquatic life found in these
                   streams require relatively cool and clean water. Potential effects of wind energy
                   development are primarily associated with forest clearing and road construction.


               35  United States Department Of The Interior Bureau Of Land Management. Instruction Memorandum No. 2003-020.  October 16,
               2002. Available at http://www.blm.gov/nhp/efoia/wo/fy03/im2003-020.htm.
               36  Virginia Department of Game and Inland Fisheries, Homepage.  Viewed Dec. 3, 2003.
               http://www.dgif.state.va.us/hunting/wma/index.html.
               37  Virginia Department of Forestry.  “Virginia’s State Forests”.  http://www.dof.virginia.gov/stforest/index.shtml . 2004.  Viewed
               September 13, 2004.
               †
                 The GIS data pertaining to this category are temporarily withheld while license agreements are negotiated.

                                                            - 16 -

 = Page 17 =







                   Forest clearing required for turbine siting, access road construction, and
                   development of power transmission corridors may contribute to alteration of the
                   critical thermal regime of these streams. Road building, use, and maintenance may
                   also contribute to stream siltation and alteration of hydrologic conditions.
                   Construction and use of low-grade roads on steep terrain or where streams
                   crossings are required may be particularly problematic.


               U NCLASSIFIED
               The category “Unclassified” includes those areas that have Class 2 or lower wind
               resource, or for which insufficient data exist to assess site suitability for utility-scale wind
               development. It is possible that some portion of this area would be classified as
               unsuitable if adequate geographic data on areas of concentrated avian use were
               available.


























































                                                            - 17 -

 = Page 18 =








               A PPENDIX    1:D       D
                                ATA  ICTIONARY
               GIS DATA DICTIONARY
               GIS DATA FOR LANDSCAPE CLASSIFICATION
               ALL SHAPEFILES IN UTM 17N NAD 27

               Originally compiled 9/14/04 by:

               Don Giecek
               19484 Running Cedar Lane
               Maidens, VA 23102
               804-749-1992

               This document should be used as a reference guide to the geographic data on the CD.
               It is not meant to replace the metadata.  Please see the metadata directory for more
               specific details regarding the geographic data.
               ______________________________________________________________________

               The following coverages were provided by U.S. Department of Agriculture Forest
               Service: George Washington and Jefferson National Forest:

               FILE NAME ON CD:             IRA_VA_UTM17
               REPRESENTING:                USFS INVENTORIED ROADLESS AREAS
               METADATA ON CD:              IRA
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             MTPLEASANT
               REPRESENTING:                USFS NATIONAL SCENIC AREA
               METADATA ON CD:              NSA
               VWEC OBTAINED:               MAY 2004
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG- CLIPPED FROM USFS’S IRA_VA_UTM17

               FILE NAME ON CD:             NFOWN
               REPRESENTING:                USFS SURFACE OWNERSHIP
               METADATA ON CD:              NFOWN
               VWEC OBTAINED:               MAY 2004
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             RNAUSFS
               REPRESENTING:                USFS RESEARCH NATURAL AREA
               METADATA ON CD:              RNA
               VWEC OBTAINED:               MAY 2004
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG- CLIPPED FROM USFS ALTPRE_RX_GW
                                            COVERAGE (MANAGEMENT PRESCRIPTIONS FROM
                                            1993 GWNF LAND MANAGEMENT PLAN)



                                                            - 18 -

 = Page 19 =







               FILE NAME ON CD:             SBA03
               REPRESENTING:                USFS SPECIAL BIOLOGICAL AREAS
               METADATA ON CD:              SBA
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             USFSOLDGROWTH
               REPRESENTING:                USFS (JEFFERSON NF ONLY) OLD GROWTH FOREST
               METADATA ON CD:              OLDGROW
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             WILDERNESSJUNE04
               REPRESENTING:                USFS WILDERNESS AREAS
               METADATA ON CD:              WILD
               VWEC OBTAINED:               JUNE 2004
               OBTAIND BY:                  DMG- PRIEST & THREE RIDGES CLIPPED FROM USFS’S
                                            IRA_VA_UTM17 COVERAGE; REMAINDER CLIPPED
                                            FROM USFS WILDERNESS COVERAGE

               FILE NAME ON CD:             GWJEFFWILDSTUDY
               REPRESENTING:                USFS RECOMMENDED WILDERNESS STUDY AREAS
               METADATA ON CD:              WILDSTUDY
               VWEC OBTAINED:               SEPTEMBER 2004
               OBTAIND BY:                  DMG- CLIPPED FROM USFS COVERAGES
                                            REPRESENTING MANAGEMENT PRESCRIPTIONS IN
                                            THE JEFFERSON AND GW NATIONAL FORESTS.

               Contact:
               James O’Hear
               George Washington and Jefferson National Forests
               112 North River Road
               Bridgewater, VA  22812
               Phone: 540-828-1566
               Email: johear@fs.fed.us
               Web: http://www.fs.fed.us/gwjnf/gisdatadictionary.html

               Coverage Limitations:  Coverages may or may not be complete within National Forest
               ownership boundaries. Coverages are considered incomplete outside National Forest
               ownership boundaries. Updates may be applied without notice. Users are advised to
               fully and carefully read the Liability Disclaimer before downloading or using this data.

               User Responsibilities:  It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data
               appropriately and in accordance with the limitations of geospatial data in general and
               these data in particular. These data are not recommended to be used with data of
               scales larger than 1:24,000.



                                                            - 19 -

 = Page 20 =







               Liability Disclaimer:  The Forest Service cannot assure the accuracy, completeness,
               reliability, or suitability of this information for any particular purpose. Using GIS data for
               purposes other than those for which they were created may yield inaccurate or
               misleading results. The recipient may neither assert any proprietary rights to this
               information nor represent it to anyone as other than U.S. Government-produced
               information. The Forest Service shall not be liable for any activity involving this
               information with respect to lost profits, lost savings or any other consequential
               damages.
               ______________________________________________________________________

               The following coverages were provided by the Department of Conservation and
               Recreation, Conservation Lands Database:

               FILE NAME ON CD:             BLUERP
               REPRESENTING:                BLUE RIDGE PARKWAY
               METADATA ON CD:              NPS
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG- CLIPPED FROM VA DCR’S NPS COVERAGE

               FILE NAME ON CD:             DCR
               REPRESENTING:                DCR STATE PARKS AND STATE DEDICATED NATURAL
                                            AREA PRESERVE BOUNDARIES
               METADATA ON CD:              DCR
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             DGIF
               REPRESENTING:                STATE WILDLIFE MANAGEMENT AREA BOUNDARIES
               METADATA ON CD:              DGIF
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             DOF
               REPRESENTING:                VA DEPARTMENT OF FORESTRY STATE FOREST
                                            OWNERSHIP BOUNDARIES
               METADATA ON CD:              DOF
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             SNP_UTM17
               REPRESENTING:                SHENADOAH NATIONAL PARK OWNERSHIP
               METADATA ON CD:              NPS
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG- CLIPPED FROM VA DCR’S NPS COVERAGE





                                                            - 20 -

 = Page 21 =







               FILE NAME ON CD:             USFWS
               REPRESENTING:                U.S. FISH AND WILDLIFE SERVICE’S NATIONAL
                                            WILDLIFE REFUGE BOUNDARIES
               METADATA ON CD:              USFWS
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             VOF
               REPRESENTING: VIRGINIA OUTDOORS FOUNDATION EASEMENTS AND
                                            LAND HOLDINGS.
               METADATA ON CD:              VOF
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             NHR_SCREEN
               REPRESENTING:                DCR NATURAL HERITAGE RESOURCES
               METADATA ON CD:              NHR_SCREEN
               VWEC OBTAINED:               SEPTEMBER 2004
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               Contact:
               David Boyd
               Conservation Lands GIS Planner
               DCR - Natural Heritage Division
               217 Governor Street
               Richmond, VA 23219
               Phone: 804-371-4801
               Email: dboyd@dcr.state.va.us
               Web: http://www.dcr.state.va.us
               ______________________________________________________________________

               The following coverages were provided by The Nature Conservancy of Virginia.

               FILE NAME ON CD:             SELECTED_PRESERVES.SHP
               REPRESENTING: BOUNDARIES OF SELECTED PRESERVES OWNED OR
                                            MANAGED BY THE NATURE CONSERVANCY OF
                                            VIRGINIA
               METADATA ON CD:              TNC_PRESERVES
               VWEC OBTAINED:               MAY 2005
               OBTAINED BY:                 JONATHAN MILES













                                                            - 21 -

 = Page 22 =







               FILE NAME ON CD:             SELECTED_PORTFOLIO_CLS3
               REPRESENTING:                THE NATURE CONSERVANCY ECOREGIONAL
                                            PORTFOLIO CLIPPED TO INTERSECT CLASS 3 AND
                                            ABOVE WINDS (WITH 1KM BUFFER).
               METADATA ON CD:              SELECTED_PORTFOLIO_CLS3
               VWEC OBTAINED:               AUGUST 2004
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             UNROADEDTNC_NAD27
               REPRESENTING: USFS UNINVENTORIED ROADLESS AREAS- BRUCE &
                                            GIECEK
               METADATA ON CD:              UNROAD
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               Note:
               A Geographic Information Systems based analysis was conducted by Chris Bruce
               (TNC) and Don Giecek (VWC) in fall 2003 to determine the location of large roadless
               parcels in both the Jefferson and George Washington National Forests. The most
               recent Forest Service data representing roads and Forest Service land ownership was
               evaluated to locate parcels that are: 1) Greater than 1000 acres and adjacent to existing
               Wilderness or Inventoried Roadless Areas (IRA), or 2) Greater than 5000 acres and not
               adjacent to existing Wilderness and Inventoried Roadless Areas. The 1000 and 5000
               acre criteria used in this analysis are similar to the criteria used by the Forest Service in
               the IRA-RARE II analysis.

               However, this GIS based analysis yields significant acreage that was not included in the
               IRA-RARE II analysis conducted by the forest service (as represented by USFS
               coverage IRA_VA_UTM17.)

               Contact:
               Chris Bruce     OR  Regarding Uninventoried
               GIS Specialist      Roadless Areas Analysis
               The Nature Conservancy of Virginia                        Don Giecek
               490 Westfield Rd     Virginia Wilderness Committee
               Charlottesville, VA 22901                          19484 Running Cedar Lane
               Phone: 434-951-0565     Maidens, VA 23102

               Email: cbruce@tnc.org    804-749-1992
               Web: http://nature.org/Virginia   giecek@aol.com
               ______________________________________________________________________











                                                            - 22 -

 = Page 23 =







               The following coverages were provided by the Virginia Institute of Marine Science:

               FILE NAME ON CD:             SAV17_NAD27
               REPRESENTING:                SUBMERGED ACQUATIC VEGETATION
               METADATA ON CD:              SAV17
               VWEC OBTAINED:               NOV 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             SAV02
               REPRESENTING:                SUBMERGED ACQUATIC VEGETATION UPDATE
               METADATA ON CD:              IRA
               VWEC OBTAINED:               MAY 2004
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               Contact:
               Marcia Berman
               Virginia Institute of Marine Science
               Gloucester Point, VA 23062
               804-684-7088
               marcia@sweethall.wetlan.vims.edu
               ______________________________________________________________________

               The following coverage was clipped from data originally provided by TrueWind
               Solutions:

               FILE NAME ON CD:             CLASS_GE3_27
               REPRESENTING:                WIND RESOURCE CLASS 3 AND ABOVE (WIND POWER
                                            @ 50 METERS; WIND >300W/m^2)
               METADATA ON CD:              TRUEWIND
               VWEC OBTAINED:               AUGUST 2004
               OBTAINED BY:                 CLIPPED FROM WIND POWER @50 M; CHRIS BRUCE,
                                            DMG

               FILE NAME ON CD:             PWR50.BMP
               REPRESENTING:                WIND POWER @ 50 METERS; WIND >300W/m^2
               METADATA ON CD:              BITMAP
               VWEC OBTAINED:               MAY 2003
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG

               Contact:
               Brent Kinal
               GIS Specialist
               AWS Scientific
               255 Fuller Road
               Albany, NY 12203-3656
               Phone: 518-437-8790



                                                            - 23 -

 = Page 24 =







               Email: bkinal@awsscientific.com
               Web: http://www.awsscientific
               ______________________________________________________________________

               The following coverage was provided by the Appalachian Trail Conference:

               FILE NAME ON CD:             ATCENTER_VA
               REPRESENTING:                APPALCAHIAN NATIONAL SCENIC TRAIL CENTERLINE
               METADATA ON CD:              ATC
               VWEC OBTAINED:               JULY 2004
               OBTAINED BY:                 MARK LOTTS, DMG

               Contact:
               Matt Robinson
               GIS Specialist
               Appalachian Trail Conference
               799 Washington Street
               Harpers Ferry, WV 25425
               Phone: 304-535-4010
               Email: mrobinson@appalachiantrail.org
               Web: http://www.appalachiantrail.
               HYPERLINK "http://www.appalachiantrail.org/" \t "_blank"
               ______________________________________________________________________

               The following coverage was provided by the Southern Appalachian Forest Coalition:

               FILE NAME ON CD:             VIRGINIABILL_UTM17_NAD27
               REPRESENTING: VIRGINIA RIDGE AND VALLEY WILDERNESS AND
                                            NATIONAL SCENIC ACT OF 2004 (S. 2342 AND HB. 4202)
               METADATA ON CD:              VIRGINIABILL_UTM17_NAD27
               VWEC OBTAINED:               JULY 2004
               OBTAINED BY:                 DMG- PROVIDED  BY HUGH IRWIN/SAFC
               Contact:
               Hugh Irwin
               GIS Analyst
               Southern Appalachian Forest Coalition
               Asheville, NC
               Phone: 828-252-9223
               Email: hugh@safc.org
               ______________________________________________________________________

               Notes:
               1) Most coverages have been assigned new names.  Therefore, file names appearing
               here don’t necessarily correspond to original names assigned by the agency or
               organization that developed the data.  2) DMG= DONALD M. GIECEK.
               _____________________________________________________________________



                                                            - 24 -

 = Page 25 =








                                                                      E
                                                    V
                                                                                C
               A PPENDIX    2:M  EMBERS OF THE  IRGINIA        W IND  NERGY  OLLABORATIVE

               E NVIRONMENTAL       W ORKING    G ROUP

                                                     D.D        B
                                                         ANIEL  OONE
                                                    J UDY  K.D
                                                              UNSCOMB
                                                             G
                                                        D ON  IECEK
                                                        R ICK  W EBB

                                                      C HRISTINA  W ULF


                                                       Representing:


                                            The Virginia Society of Ornithology
                                                 The Nature Conservancy

                                           The Virginia Wilderness Committee
                                                   Virginia Forest Watch




               The Virginia Wind Energy Collaborative offers special thanks to Mr. Giecek and to Mr.
               Mark Lotts of VWEC for their significant contributions toward the completion of the GIS-
               based component of this resource. Mr. Giecek served as the principal architect of the
               GIS data resource and was a significant contributor toward development of the LCS. Mr.
               Lotts provided considerable technical assistance and guidance during development of
               the GIS database.





























                                                            - 25 -

 = Page 26 =
