
               SYNOPSIS OF THE VIRGINIA CONSERVATION LANDS NEEDS ASSESSMENT

               The VCLNA is a flexible, widely applicable tool for integrating and coordinating the needs and strategies
               of different conservation interests, using GIS (Geographic Information System) to model and map land
               conservation priorities and actions in Virginia.  The VCLNA consists of seven complex models:


                              ECOLOGICAL MODEL
                              The  Ecological Model  is a collection of models and products including the Virginia Natural
                              Landscape Assessment (VaNLA), DGIF’s Wildlife Action Plan, and a biodiversity assessment using
                              species and natural community information from DCR’s Natural Heritage Program.  The VaNLA is a
                              landscape-scale GIS analysis for identifying, prioritizing, and linking natural habitats in Virginia.  It
                              identifies and connects the most important natural, unfragmented lands based on considerations of
                              biological and ecological value and integrity.

                              CULTURAL ASSET MODEL
                              The  Virginia Cultural Asset Model  is a statewide model showing the cultural value of lands in
                              Virginia.  The Division of Natural Heritage worked closely with the Virginia Department of Historic
                              Resources to identify and prioritize important cultural assets in Virginia, including archaeological
                              and architectural sites, and American Indian Areas.

                              VULNERABILITY MODEL
                              The  Virginia Vulnerability Model  (or growth prediction model) are four statewide and one
                              composite model showing predicted growth patterns across the landscape.  The model uses GIS
                              and statistical methods to analyze housing allocation, lot size estimation, growth hotspot,
                              residential land conversion hotspots and travel time proximity in an effort to model urban, suburban
                              (urban fringe) and rural (outside the urban fringe) growth patterns.


                               FOREST ECONOMICS MODEL
                               The  Forest Economics Model  is a GIS effort to map viable forestland with economic value.  The
                               Division worked closely with the Virginia Department of Forestry to analyze biophysical
                               parameters, management constraints and socioeconomic influences.


                               RECREATION MODEL
                               The  Virginia Recreation Model  is a GIS effort to map the value of lands as they contribute to
                               recreational opportunity.  The Division worked closely with the Virginia Department of Game and
                               Inland Fisheries as well as DCR’s Division of Planning and Recreation and numerous
                               collaborators and data contributors to analyze a variety of recreational datasets (including but not
                               limited to hunting, fishing, wildlife watching, parks, trails, population density influences and public
                               access) in an effort to model recreational value across the landscape.

                                WATERSHED INTEGRITY MODEL
                                The  Virginia Watershed Integrity Model  is a GIS effort to map the relative value of land as it
                                contributes to water quality and watershed integrity.  The Division worked closely with the
                                Virginia Department of Forestry and Virginia Commonwealth University Center for Environmental
                                Studies to analyze a variety of parameters focused on identifying important terrestrial features
                                that contribute to water resources, and, therefore watershed integrity.


                                AGRICULTURAL MODEL
                                The  Virginia Agricultural Model  is a GIS effort to map important agricultural lands in Virginia,
                                developed in cooperation with the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services and the
                                Virginia Department of Historic Resources.  This model analyzed parameters such as soils,
                                slope, land use and historic farms.









                                                            http://www.dcr.virginia.gov/natural_heritage/vclna.shtml

 = Page 1 =
