








             Comparing Virginia’s Scenic Rivers Program to federal programs
             Many states have, or are looking to develop, a scenic rivers designation program, but Virginia’s is one of the
             oldest. Often, however, it is confused with other designation programs, especially  national programs .


             Scenic River Designations

                        TITLE   National Wild and Scenic   American Heritage Rivers   Virginia Scenic Rivers
                              River System               Initiative                 Program
             MISSION/ INTENT                                                        to identify, designate and
                                                         to foster community        enhance the protection rivers
                                                                                    and streams that possess
                                                         empowerment, help protect   outstanding scenic, cultural,
                              to protect designated river   and restore the environment,   recreational, historic and
                              segments                   revitalize the economy,    natural characteristics of
                                                         renew the culture and      statewide significance for
                                                         preserve history.          future generations through

                                                                                    wise use and conservation
                DESIGNATION U.S. Congress or the
                       FROM Secretary of the Interior    Presidential decree        Virginia General Assembly
             ADMINISTRATOR                               Environmental Protection   Virginia Department of
                              National Park Service      Agency                     Conservation and Recreation
              DATE ENACTED 1968                          1997                       1970
                 NUMBER OF    156 (2004); none in Virginia   14; New and Potomac in   30; 728+ miles
                      RIVERS                             Virginia
               CRITERIA FOR                                                         river corridor vegetation, flow
                DESIGNATION                              distinctive inherent       modifications, human
                              possessing outstanding or   characteristics of river,   development, historic, cultural,
                              remarkable scenic,         effective community plan of   landscape, quality of fishery,
                              recreational, geological,   action, strength and diversity  endangered species, water
                              natural, historical, cultural,   of community support,   quality, parallel roads,
                              or other similar values    partnerships capability    crossings, special features,

                                                                                    and aesthetics
               AREA DEFINED within 1/4 mile of ordinary   none                      river bottom to ordinary low-
                              high-water mark                                       water mark
                    IMPACTS/                             more effective use of federal
              RESTRICTIONS free-flowing condition and    resources with help of River  No dams may be put on the
                              are not dammed or          Navigator to facilitate    river without General Assembly
                              otherwise improved.        community-agency           action
                                                         interchange
                MANAGER OF ACOE, BLM, NPS, USFS,
                  CORRIDOR USFWS and various states      localities                 localities
                    FUNDING through managers             none                       none
                HOW TO ADD  any time with complete
                              report and acceptance of   through congressional      request from locality and
                                                         decree
                                                                                    complete report
                              management plan
                 ADDITIONAL
               INFORMATION                                                          http://www.dcr.virginia.gov/recr
                              http://www.nps.gov/rivers/    http://www.epa.gov/rivers/
                                                                                    eational_planning/srmain.shtml


                                                                                                   Revised: 09/13/13

 = Page 1 =
