<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Virginia Dept. of Conservation and Recreation - DSWC</origin>
				<pubdate>20040816</pubdate>
				<title>Flight Area Counties</title>
				<edition>2004</edition>
				<geoform Sync="TRUE">vector digital data</geoform>
				<serinfo>
					<sername>jurisdiction boundaries</sername>
					<issue>2004 update</issue>
				</serinfo>
				<pubinfo>
					<pubplace>Richmond, Virginia</pubplace>
					<publish>Virginia DCR-DSWC</publish>
				</pubinfo>
				<othercit>Basis is the USGS 7.5 minute topo quad DRGs</othercit>
				<ftname Sync="TRUE">flight_area_counties</ftname></citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>
Jurisdiction boundaries for all counties (95) and cities (39) in Virginia
at a precision that is, at a minimum, from heads-up digitizing off of DRGs.
</abstract>
			<purpose>
These are the jurisdiction boundaries used by Virginia DCR to geocode
any geographic information with a jurisdiction FIPS code.  They were
developed prior to, and for, the development of Virginia's 14 digit
hydrologic unit boundaries and updated from 2002-2004 as part of the
development of the National Watershed Boundary Dataset (NWBD).
</purpose>
			<supplinf>
Origin:

Version 1 jurisdiction boundaries were originally digitized at ISSL,
VPI&amp;SU in 1989 off of the USGS 7.5 minute quadrangle maps.  Some
modifications were made at that time given the date of some quads.
The line and attribute data were delivered to the VA DCR in DLG3 format.

Revisions:

Version 1995:
Version 1995 was made at the Virginia DCR, using version 1 as a base,
as part of the development of Virginia's 14 digit hydrologic unit layer.
At that time the jurisdiction boundaries were updated using newer quad
maps or maps supplied by various jurisdictions and the Virginia DOT,
all of which were at a better scale than the quads but were not always
done to map accuracy standards.  These newly digitized products were used
to replace older existing boundaries.  Changes were made to the
boundaries of 34 jurisdictions between the first and 1995 versions.

Version 2004:
Version 2004 varies from version 1995 in many ways.  The major differences
are that almost all of the linework has been recaptured at a better
resolution, and linework has been added to delineate what is in a
jurisdiction from what a local government has jurisdiction over.  The
improved resolution was realized by overlaying the linework of version 1995
onto enhanced DRGs and recapturing linework via heads-up digitizing on
images which are enlarged beyond the 1:24,000 scale of the original paper
maps.  The determinations of what areas of the state are truly within any
local jurisdictions versus being within the state but outside of all local
jurisdictions was assisted by the Virginia Attorney General's Office.

Additionally, as these boundaries were being recaptured as part of the
NWBD development, jurisdiction boundaries that coexisted as watershed
boundaries were modified to align with the watershed boundaries as they
were defined in the NWBD versus aligning with jurisdiction boundaries
as they were drawn on the USGS topographic quads.  These situations are
noted in the line attribute table.

Other than the improved linework due to the DRG use and NWBD development
as noted above, the following changes were made between versions 1995 and
2004:
(1) Clifton Forge is removed as it is no longer a city. (2) The shoreline
boundaries of jurisdictions bordering the Chesapeake Bay and Atlantic Ocean
have been recaptured off of DOQQs. (3) The offshore waters of Virginia have
been added to the 3 nautical mile limit. (4) The boundary between Prince
George and Sussex and between Sussex and Surry has been altered (Disputanta
South quad). (5) The boundary of Emporia has been altered. (6) The boundary
between Lynchburg and Amherst was altered. (7) The boundary between Danville
and Pittsylvania Co was altered. (8) The boundary of Williamsburg has been
altered based on its representation on their web site. (9) The state
boundary has been altered from Smith Point to Rhodes Point.  In particular,
it originates further southeast on the line extending from Smith Point than
previously portrayed on 7.5 minute topo maps. (10) The boundary between
Fauquier and Prince William has been altered. (11) The boundary between
Giles and Monroe County, WV has been altered. (12) The boundary between
Louisa and Goochland was altered to reflect the boundary as displayed on
VDOT county maps. (13) Minor adjustments were made to the boundary of
Norton. (14) Minor adjustments were made to the boundary of Bristol.

Territorial waters within the Commonwealth have been determined with the
assistance of the Virginia Attorney General's Office.  As advised by that
office, and in accordance with section 15.2-3105 of the Code of Virginia,
Chesapeake Bay waters, Atlantic Ocean waters, and the tidal tributaries to
these bodies of water, are not considered part of any local jurisdiction.
In other words, "the normal activities of counties and cities do not extend
off shore".  Section 15.2-3105 extends the boundary of local jurisdictions
along the Chesapeake Bay or Atlantic Ocean to "embrace all wharfs, piers,
docks, and other structures, except bridges and tunnels that have been or
may hereafter be erected along the waterfront".  Therefore shorelines that
include these structures are now used to define the jurisdiction
boundaries along the Chesapeake Bay and Atlantic Ocean.  While tidal rivers
of these bodies are also part of this decree, it would be difficult to
accurately portray local jurisdiction boundaries excluding all tidal waters
of the Bay and the Atlantic.  It would also produce a version of jurisdiction
boundaries for Virginia unlikely to be used by the agencies of the state
who this layer is intended to assist.  Therefore, an apparent limit arc has
been added across tidal waters to delineate the Chesapeake Bay and Atlantic
Ocean proper from their tidal tributaries. These artificial boundaries have
been attributed as such.

The same legal source also advises that in accordance with Sections
16.1-69.29 and 17.1-516, the local jurisdictions of the Commonwealth have
been given "concurrent territorial jurisdiction [to the district and circuit
courts of counties on each side of any river, watercourse, or bay,] over so
much thereof as shall be opposite to such counties".  Likewise, local
jurisdictions have been authorized by Section 29.1-744.C to enact ordinances
regulating vessels and the conduct of people within the territorial limits,
including the marginal adjacent Atlantic Ocean.  This section extends the
territorial limits of the seaside jurisdictions out three miles into the
Atlantic Ocean.  Accordingly, this version of the jurisdiction boundaries
contains the delineations of the Chesapeake Bay and Atlantic Ocean as
necessary to portray these stated territorial jurisdictions, including an
equidistance mid-Bay boundary that will not align with the mid-Bay
boundary found in federal spatial layers showing jurisdiction boundaries
in Virginia.

It is possible to only display the arcs defining jurisdictions, versus also
showing arcs which only define areas that jurisdictions have jurisdiction
over.  One method would be to dissolve this shapefile on the fips and/or
fips2 field.  Dissolving on fips will create a new polygon shapefile
containing areas within the local jurisdiction.  This shapefile will have
a separate polygon for the Chesapeake Bay and the Atlantic territorial
waters.  Dissolving on fips2 will result in a new polygon shapefile
containing all the areas which the local jurisdictions have jurisdiction
over.  This is particularly relevant if you are using ArcView.
</supplinf>
			<langdata Sync="TRUE">en</langdata></descript>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<rngdates>
					<begdate>20010801</begdate>
					<enddate>present</enddate>
				</rngdates>
			</timeinfo>
			<current>Publication date of sources</current>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Complete</progress>
			<update>
Updated whenever known boundary changes are made and maps of said changes
can be obtained.  However, there is no process in place to assure that DCR
is aware of such changes when they occur.

Upcoming modifications will include the infusion of boundaries from
local governments where those boundaries are agreeable to parties on
both sides, ridge modifications from more precise topographic sources,
and more current and precise shorelines from the hydrography developed
from the VA Base Map Imagery.
</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc Sync="TRUE">-83.837830</westbc>
				<eastbc Sync="TRUE">-75.160162</eastbc>
				<northbc Sync="TRUE">39.471482</northbc>
				<southbc Sync="TRUE">36.464993</southbc>
			</bounding>
			<lboundng><leftbc Sync="TRUE">-373533.600000</leftbc><rightbc Sync="TRUE">373706.800000</rightbc><bottombc Sync="TRUE">60037.600000</bottombc><topbc Sync="TRUE">385287.800000</topbc></lboundng></spdom>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekt>none</themekt>
				<themekey>jurisdiction</themekey>
				<themekey>cities</themekey>
				<themekey>counties</themekey>
			</theme>
			<place>
				<placekt>none</placekt>
				<placekey>Virginia</placekey>
			</place>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>none</accconst>
		<useconst>Crediting VA DCR for dataset development is requested.</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Karl Huber</cntper>
					<cntorg>Virginia Dept. of Conservation &amp; Recreation - DSWC</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
					<address>203 Governor Street, Suite 206</address>
					<city>Richmond</city>
					<state>Virginia</state>
					<postal>23219-2094</postal>
					<country>USA</country>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>804 371 7484</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>804 371 2630</cntfax>
				<cntemail>karl.huber@dcr.virginia.gov</cntemail>
				<hours>0830-1800</hours>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
		<datacred>
DCR-DSWC is credited with the linework revisions of version 1995.  The almost
complete redigitizing of version 2004 from DRGs was done by Virginia Tech -
Biological Systems Engineering staff working at DCR-DSWC.  Legal assistance
was provided by Frederick Fisher, Senior Assistant Attorney General in the
Virginia Office of the Attorney General.
</datacred>
		<native Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.1850</native>
		<crossref>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>ISSL</origin>
				<pubdate>1989</pubdate>
				<title>Virginia's jurisdiction boundaries</title>
				<edition>1</edition>
				<geoform>map</geoform>
				<serinfo>
					<sername>jurisdiction boundaries</sername>
					<issue>version 1</issue>
				</serinfo>
				<pubinfo>
					<pubplace>Blacksburg, Virginia</pubplace>
					<publish>ISSL</publish>
				</pubinfo>
			</citeinfo>
		</crossref>
		<crossref>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>VDOT</origin>
				<pubdate>19930101</pubdate>
				<title>County Road Map Atlas</title>
				<edition>1993</edition>
				<geoform>map</geoform>
				<serinfo>
					<sername>County Road Map Atlas</sername>
					<issue>1993 Volume</issue>
				</serinfo>
				<pubinfo>
					<pubplace>Richmond, Virginia</pubplace>
					<publish>VDOT</publish>
				</pubinfo>
			</citeinfo>
		</crossref>
		<crossref>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>VDOT</origin>
				<pubdate>1992</pubdate>
				<title>City Road Maps</title>
				<edition>1991</edition>
				<geoform>map</geoform>
				<serinfo>
					<sername>City Road Map</sername>
					<issue>1991 Volume</issue>
				</serinfo>
				<pubinfo>
					<pubplace>Richmond, Virginia</pubplace>
					<publish>VDOT</publish>
				</pubinfo>
			</citeinfo>
		</crossref>
		<crossref>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>USDA-NRCS</origin>
				<pubdate>2000</pubdate>
				<title>Enhanced DRGs of Virginia</title>
				<edition>2000</edition>
				<geoform>map</geoform>
				<serinfo>
					<sername>Enhanced DRGs</sername>
					<issue>Virginia Quads</issue>
				</serinfo>
				<pubinfo>
					<pubplace>Ft Worth, Texas</pubplace>
					<publish>USDA-NRCS</publish>
				</pubinfo>
			</citeinfo>
		</crossref>
		<natvform Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</natvform></idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<attracc>
			<attraccr>
Jurisdiction FIPS code assignment to the polygons of this dataset are
correct except as noted here.
(1)The code of Virginia does not assign the Chespaeake Bay waters to
local jurisdictions.  Therefore, the bay polygon has been assigned the
fabricated FIPS code of 901 by DCR.  Likewise, the offshore Atlantic
waters within the 3 mile zone are assigned the fabricated FIPS code of
903. (2)The Hampton Roads area has been assigned as an area which Hampton
has jurisdiction over, based on best available sources.  (3)The state
FIPS code (51) is not appended to any local jurisdiction FIPS code.
</attraccr>
		</attracc>
		<logic>
All arcs are used to define jurisdiction boundaries or areas of assigned
jurisdiction.  There are no dangling arcs, nor does any polygon contain more
than one label.  There are, however, more polygons than there are
jurisdictions because the shoreline is being used to define jurisdiction
boundaries along the Atlantic and in the Chesapeake Bay.  Thus many islands
which are not connected to the mainland now appear as separate polygons of
jurisdictions.
</logic>
		<complete>
This dataset is in need of additional refinement, including the following.
(1) While it has been concluded that the Bay and Atlantic waters are not part
of any jurisdiction in Virginia except the state itself, the border between
the jurisdictions of Virginia and the state owned waters of the Bay and
Atlantic is always fluctuating.  Using shorelines as boundaries in this layer
was limited to defining (a) the Chesapeake Bay from the tidal rivers and any
adjoining land, and (b) the barrier islands of the Atlantic shore from the
ocean.  DOQQs were used for this task.  The DOQQ for the northeast corner of
the Tangier Island quad was insufficient for capturing the shorelines of the
islands in that area.  That portion of the south Potomac River shore which
defines the border between Virginia and Maryland should also have been captured
from DOQQs.  Shore linework will eventually be replaced by the shorelines in
the hydrography portion of the Virginia Base Map product.  (2) Buena Vista
boundaries (and the related portion of Rockbridge County boundaries) are
approximate due to incomplete base maps.  (3) No town boundaries are included
in this coverage.  They would be a welcome addition if a process to update and
maintain them can be arranged.  (4) Adjoining states claim boundaries which do
not always coincide with the state boundary of Virginia as found in this layer.
Attempts to resolve these discrepancies have been complicated by the lack of
knowledge and documentation held by the agencies of these states on the
source of the boundaries which they use.  Furthermore, as in Virginia, there
is more than one version of the boundaries of these states being used by the
various state agencies of those states and by various federal agencies.
</complete>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>
The accuracy of boundaries for jurisdictions as they appear on the 7.5
minute quadrangle maps is unknown.  USGS map accuracy standards for
the 7.5 minute quadrangles would indicate minimumal distortion.
However, it is apparent that jurisdiction boundaries which might be
intended to be coterminous with ridge lines do not always follow the
ridge lines as defined during Virginia's watershed boundary delineations
as performed on DRGs.  It is unclear as to whether or not these
jurisdiction boundaries should therefore  be moved to where DCR has
delineated watershed boundaries.  Such adjustments have been performed in
this version but noted where they have occurred due to the indecision.
Other potential problems are due to the age of the source maps rather
than in the cartographic representation of the boundaries as made on the
maps.  The latest seamless DRGs were used in this task.  Boundaries from
these 7.5 minute maps were compared to those defined in the VDOT county
and city map series.  Inconsistencies were researched to determine the
most accurate representation.  While resulting accuracies are sufficient
for work at the state scope, they are not as accurate as those that
could be developed by the jurisdictions themselves in some cases.
Some updates were done from maps which could not attain minimal RMS
error when digitized.  Updates to linework performed in version 2004
produced improved accuracies due to the ability to capture linework off
of zoomed-in DRGs.  Updates to the shorelines, however, are even more
current and precise since they were captured from DOQQs.  Atlantic and
Chesapeake Bay shore boundaries are always changing, however, due to
rapidly shifting sands and tidal fluctuations.  Therefore all shorelines
are approximate despite attempts to capture them in detail.  Similar
erosion based changes occur along the many stretches of the southern
shoreline of the Potomac River that define the boundary between Virginia
and Maryland.  An issue which arises from this erosion is whether or not
the boundary changes along with the shoreline.  Discussions with state
employees who were deemed to have some knowledge of this issue indicates
that they do.
</horizpar>
				<qhorizpa>
					<horizpav>0.61 meters</horizpav>
					<horizpae>ground distance resolution</horizpae>
				</qhorizpa>
			</horizpa>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>ISSL</origin>
						<pubdate>1989</pubdate>
						<title>VirGIS jurisdiction boundaries, version 1</title>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srcscale>24000</srcscale>
				<typesrc>USGS 7.5 minute quads</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<rngdates>
							<begdate>1949</begdate>
							<enddate>1987</enddate>
						</rngdates>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>out of date</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>1989 jurisdiction bounds</srccitea>
				<srccontr>base upon which updates were made for version 1995</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>DCR-DSWC</origin>
						<pubdate>1995</pubdate>
						<title>VirGIS jurisdiction boundaries, version 1995</title>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srcscale>24000</srcscale>
				<typesrc>USGS 7.5 minute quads</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<rngdates>
							<begdate>1949</begdate>
							<enddate>1987</enddate>
						</rngdates>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>out of date</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>1995 jurisdiction bounds</srccitea>
				<srccontr>base upon which updates were made for version 2004</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>
Digitize - the refined linework for jurisdiction boundaries and
6th order hydrologic unit (hu) boundaries was captured by overlaying
version 1995 of the jurisdiction/hu dataset on enhanced DRGs and
performing heads-up digitizing of linework needing refinement.
</procdesc>
				<procdate>200208</procdate>
				<proccont>
					<cntinfo>
						<cntperp>
							<cntper>Gina Beale</cntper>
							<cntorg>VA DCR-DSWC</cntorg>
						</cntperp>
					</cntinfo>
				</proccont>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>
Update - where city/county boundaries had been changed since the date
of the DRG publications, the previously captured linework of these
changes were inserted into the refined linework.  If changes had not
been previously captured, the best representation of those changes were
obtained and captured, after which they were added to this dataset.
</procdesc>
				<procdate>200210</procdate>
				<proccont>
					<cntinfo>
						<cntperp>
							<cntper>Gina Beale and Andrea Styles</cntper>
							<cntorg>VA DCR-DSWC</cntorg>
						</cntperp>
					</cntinfo>
				</proccont>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>
Additions - mid-Bay boundary was created via spatial processing.
Other open water boundaries were added, including those in Atlantic.
</procdesc>
				<procdate>200302</procdate>
				<proccont>
					<cntinfo>
						<cntperp>
							<cntper>Andrea Styles</cntper>
							<cntorg>VA DCR-DSWC</cntorg>
						</cntperp>
					</cntinfo>
				</proccont>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>
Label Attribution - FIPS codes were added to the polygon attribute
table during editing.  This included the FIPS of the jurisdiction which
the polygon lied within and the FIPS of the jurisdiction which the
courts of said jurisdiction have jurisdiction over.
</procdesc>
				<procdate>200404</procdate>
				<proccont>
					<cntinfo>
						<cntperp>
							<cntper>Gina Beale</cntper>
							<cntorg>VA DCR-DSWC</cntorg>
						</cntperp>
					</cntinfo>
				</proccont>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>
Attribute Arcs - the boundary lines of this data set were attributed
with references to the source of each arc.
</procdesc>
				<procdate>200407</procdate>
				<proccont>
					<cntinfo>
						<cntperp>
							<cntper>Gina Beale</cntper>
							<cntorg>VA DCR-DSWC</cntorg>
						</cntperp>
					</cntinfo>
				</proccont>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>
Project - the joint jurisdiction boundary &amp; NWBD boundary cover was
projected from the UTM plane coordinate system (latest zone to be edited)
to the Lambert projection.
</procdesc>
				<procdate>200408</procdate>
				<proccont>
					<cntinfo>
						<cntperp>
							<cntper>Gina Beale</cntper>
							<cntorg>VA DCR-DSWC</cntorg>
						</cntperp>
					</cntinfo>
				</proccont>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>
Dissolve - this data set created by dissolving (on FIPS and FIPS2) the
the cover of combined jurisdiction and watershed boundaries as digitized
for NWBD development in Virginia.
</procdesc>
				<procdate>200408</procdate>
				<proccont>
					<cntinfo>
						<cntperp>
							<cntper>Gina Beale</cntper>
							<cntorg>VA DCR-DSWC</cntorg>
						</cntperp>
					</cntinfo>
				</proccont>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>
Project - the standard version of the cover of this layer was projected
to decimal degrees for eventual use in ArcView.
</procdesc>
				<procdate>200408</procdate>
				<proccont>
					<cntinfo>
						<cntperp>
							<cntper>Gina Beale</cntper>
							<cntorg>VA DCR-DSWC</cntorg>
						</cntperp>
					</cntinfo>
				</proccont>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>
Format Conversion - the decimal degree version of the cover of this
layer was converted to a shapefile using the ARCSHAPE command.
</procdesc>
				<procdate>200408</procdate>
				<proccont>
					<cntinfo>
						<cntperp>
							<cntper>Gina Beale</cntper>
							<cntorg>VA DCR-DSWC</cntorg>
						</cntperp>
					</cntinfo>
				</proccont>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<direct Sync="TRUE">Vector</direct>
		<ptvctinf>
			<sdtsterm Name="flight_area_counties">
				<sdtstype Sync="TRUE">G-polygon</sdtstype>
				<ptvctcnt Sync="TRUE">134</ptvctcnt>
			</sdtsterm>
			<sdtsterm>
				<sdtstype>String</sdtstype>
				<ptvctcnt>1119</ptvctcnt>
			</sdtsterm>
			<sdtsterm>
				<sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype>
				<ptvctcnt>174</ptvctcnt>
			</sdtsterm>
			<esriterm Name="flight_area_counties"><efeatyp Sync="TRUE">Simple</efeatyp><efeageom Sync="TRUE">Polygon</efeageom><esritopo Sync="TRUE">FALSE</esritopo><efeacnt Sync="TRUE">134</efeacnt><spindex Sync="TRUE">FALSE</spindex><linrefer Sync="TRUE">FALSE</linrefer></esriterm></ptvctinf>
	</spdoinfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn Sync="TRUE">North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
				<ellips Sync="TRUE">Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
				<semiaxis Sync="TRUE">6378137.000000</semiaxis>
				<denflat Sync="TRUE">298.257222</denflat>
			</geodetic>
			<cordsysn><geogcsn Sync="TRUE">GCS_North_American_1983</geogcsn><projcsn Sync="TRUE">Lambert_Conformal_Conic_Virginia</projcsn></cordsysn><planar><planci><plance Sync="TRUE">coordinate pair</plance><plandu Sync="TRUE">meters</plandu><coordrep><absres Sync="TRUE">0.000000</absres><ordres Sync="TRUE">0.000000</ordres></coordrep></planci><mapproj><mapprojn Sync="TRUE">Lambert Conformal Conic</mapprojn><lambertc><stdparll Sync="TRUE">37.000000</stdparll><stdparll Sync="TRUE">39.500000</stdparll><longcm Sync="TRUE">-79.500000</longcm><latprjo Sync="TRUE">36.000000</latprjo><feast Sync="TRUE">0.000000</feast><fnorth Sync="TRUE">0.000000</fnorth></lambertc></mapproj></planar></horizsys>
		<vertdef><altsys><altenc Sync="TRUE">Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc><altres Sync="TRUE">1.000000</altres></altsys></vertdef></spref>
	<eainfo>
		<detailed Name="flight_area_counties">
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>SHAPE</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>feature type</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>polyline</edomv>
						<edomvd>line defining polygon</edomvd>
						<edomvds>ESRI</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Geometry</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">0</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr>
			<enttyp>
				<enttypl Sync="TRUE">flight_area_counties</enttypl>
				<enttypd>attributes of lines in shapefile</enttypd>
				<enttypds>ESRI</enttypds>
				<enttypt Sync="TRUE">Feature Class</enttypt><enttypc Sync="TRUE">134</enttypc></enttyp>
			<attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">Area</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">Year</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">5</attwidth><attrdef>Flight Area</attrdef><attrdefs>VGIN</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>East</edomv><edomvd>Eastern flight zone</edomvd><edomvds>VGIN</edomvds></edom><edom><edomv>West</edomv><edomvd>Western flight zone</edomvd><edomvds>VGIN</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">Year</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">SP_Zone</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Number</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">9</attwidth><attrdef>Flight Year</attrdef><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>2009</edomv><edomvd>2009 Flight Area</edomvd><edomvds>VGIN</edomvds></edom><edom><edomv>2011</edomv><edomvd>2011 Flight Area</edomvd><edomvds>VGIN</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">SP_Zone</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">NAME</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">10</attwidth><attrdef>Virginia State Plane Zone</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>North</edomv><edomvd>Virginia State Plane North Zone</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>South</edomv><edomvd>Virginia State Plane South Zone</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">NAME</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">CFIPS</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">128</attwidth><attrdef>Name of City or County</attrdef><attrdomv><udom>Character Field</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">CFIPS</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">FID</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">5</attwidth><attrdef>FIPS Code</attrdef><attrdomv><udom>Character Field</udom></attrdomv><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs></attr></detailed>
	</eainfo>
	<distinfo>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Karl Huber</cntper>
					<cntorg>Virginia Dept. of Conservation &amp; Recreation - DSWC</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
					<address>203 Governor Street, Suite 206</address>
					<city>Richmond</city>
					<state>Virginia</state>
					<postal>23219-2094</postal>
					<country>USA</country>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>804 371 7484</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>804 371 2630</cntfax>
				<cntemail>karl.huber@dcr.virginia.gov</cntemail>
				<hours>0830-1800</hours>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
		<resdesc>statewide 1:24000 jurisdiction boundaries</resdesc>
		<distliab>none</distliab>
		<stdorder>
			<digform>
				<digtinfo>
					<formname>shapefile made from ARC/INFO cover</formname>
					<formvern>3.3</formvern>
					<filedec>
All files of the shapefile and related database tables have been
compressed and collected into a ZIP file.  Uncompress on XP or use
WinZip.
</filedec>
					<transize>6.15 MB for all files of shapefile</transize>
					<dssize Sync="TRUE">4.391</dssize></digtinfo>
				<digtopt>
					<onlinopt>
						<computer>
							<networka>
								<networkr>DCR ftp site</networkr>
							</networka>
						</computer>
						<accinstr>
Email distribution contact to request this data via ftp.
Instructions for retrieval will be sent back.
</accinstr>
						<oncomp>Sun Enterprise with Solaris (UNIX).</oncomp>
					</onlinopt>
				</digtopt>
			</digform>
			<fees>none</fees>
			<ordering>may be ordered by phone but email preferred</ordering>
			<turnarnd>a couple of days max if requeseted in native form</turnarnd>
		</stdorder>
		<custom>
If you cannot use this layer in the stated projection and datum, and
you cannot reproject it yourself, it can  be requested from DCR in
another projection.
</custom>
	</distinfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd Sync="TRUE">20081210</metd>
		<metrd>20040830</metrd>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Karl Huber</cntper>
					<cntorg>Virginia Dept. of Conservation &amp; Recreation - DSWC</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
					<address>203 Governor Street, Suite 206</address>
					<city>Richmond</city>
					<state>Virginia</state>
					<postal>23219-2094</postal>
					<country>USA</country>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>804 371 7484</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>804 371 2630</cntfax>
				<cntemail>karl.huber@dcr.virginia.gov</cntemail>
				<hours>0830-1800</hours>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
		<metstdn Sync="TRUE">FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
		<metstdv Sync="TRUE">FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
		<metac>none</metac>
		<langmeta Sync="TRUE">en</langmeta><mettc Sync="TRUE">local time</mettc><metextns><onlink Sync="TRUE">http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink><metprof Sync="TRUE">ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof></metextns></metainfo>
	<Esri><CreaDate>20081210</CreaDate><CreaTime>13483800</CreaTime><SyncOnce>FALSE</SyncOnce><SyncDate>20081210</SyncDate><SyncTime>14021100</SyncTime><ModDate>20081210</ModDate><ModTime>14253600</ModTime><DataProperties><lineage><Process Name="FeatureClassToFeatureClass_1" ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Conversion Tools.tbx\FeatureClassToFeatureClass" Date="20070416" Time="113104">FeatureClassToFeatureClass F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\flight_areas.mdb county_boundaries # "OBJECTID OBJECTID true false false 10 Double 0 10 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,OBJECTID,-1,-1;NAME NAME true false false 128 Text 0 0 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,NAME,-1,-1;CFIPS CFIPS true false false 5 Text 0 0 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,CFIPS,-1,-1;CFIPS_NUM CFIPS_NUM true false false 10 Double 0 10 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,CFIPS_NUM,-1,-1;PDC PDC true false false 5 Long 0 5 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,PDC,-1,-1;DEQ DEQ true false false 5 Long 0 5 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,DEQ,-1,-1;PDCNAME PDCNAME true false false 50 Text 0 0 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,PDCNAME,-1,-1;SWCD SWCD true false false 5 Long 0 5 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,SWCD,-1,-1;TECH_COUNC TECH_COUNC true false false 60 Text 0 0 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,TECH_COUNC,-1,-1;REG_ECDEV REG_ECDEV true false false 60 Text 0 0 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,REG_ECDEV,-1,-1;COMM_COLL_ COMM_COLL_ true false false 60 Text 0 0 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,COMM_COLL_,-1,-1;TOBACCO TOBACCO true false false 5 Long 0 5 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,TOBACCO,-1,-1;METROSA METROSA true false false 50 Text 0 0 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,METROSA,-1,-1;MICROSA MICROSA true false false 50 Text 0 0 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,MICROSA,-1,-1;SHAPE_area SHAPE_area true false false 19 Double 0 0 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,SHAPE_area,-1,-1;SHAPE_len SHAPE_len true false false 19 Double 0 0 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,SHAPE_len,-1,-1;Lyle Lyle true false false 4 Short 0 4 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,Lyle,-1,-1;Flight Flight true false false 4 Short 0 4 ,First,#,F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\county_boundaries.shp,2009Flight,-1,-1" # F:\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\flight_areas.mdb\county_boundaries</Process></lineage></DataProperties><MetaID>{163C71A7-BC28-430A-84AF-53CA9B6FCD41}</MetaID><Sync>FALSE</Sync></Esri><dataIdInfo><envirDesc Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.2.1.1332</envirDesc><dataLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></dataLang><idCitation><resTitle Sync="TRUE">county_boundaries</resTitle><presForm><PresFormCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></PresFormCd></presForm></idCitation><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></SpatRepTypCd></spatRpType><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="native"><westBL Sync="TRUE">-373533.6</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">379400</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">385287.8</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">60037.6</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt><geoBox esriExtentType="decdegrees"><westBL Sync="TRUE">-83.83783</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-75.094146</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">39.471481</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">36.462665</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></geoBox></dataIdInfo><mdLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></mdLang><mdStanName Sync="TRUE">ISO 19115 Geographic Information - Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer Sync="TRUE">DIS_ESRI1.0</mdStanVer><mdChar><CharSetCd Sync="TRUE" value="004"></CharSetCd></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></ScopeCd></mdHrLv><mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><orDesc Sync="TRUE">002</orDesc><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\cov-rpb-nas002\vgin\VGIN\1-VBMP-imagery\VBMP2009\Planning\Flight_Areas\flight_areas.mdb</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc></distorTran><distorFormat><formatName Sync="TRUE">Personal GeoDatabase Feature Class</formatName></distorFormat></distributor></distInfo><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode Sync="TRUE">Lambert_Conformal_Conic_Virginia</identCode></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><spatRepInfo><VectSpatRep><topLvl><TopoLevCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></TopoLevCd></topLvl><geometObjs Name="county_boundaries"><geoObjTyp><GeoObjTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></GeoObjTypCd></geoObjTyp><geoObjCnt Sync="TRUE">0</geoObjCnt></geometObjs></VectSpatRep></spatRepInfo><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20070416</mdDateSt></metadata>
